<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessednesse of being bountifull, or, Our blessed Saviours usual proverb, opened, asserted, and practically improved by Simon Ford.</title>
            <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11795350</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11795350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 493:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessednesse of being bountifull, or, Our blessed Saviours usual proverb, opened, asserted, and practically improved by Simon Ford.</title>
                  <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 138 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Collins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XX, 35 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BLESSEDNESSE OF BEING BOUNTIFULL: OR, Our Bleſſed Saviours uſual PROVERB, Opened, Aſſerted, and Practically Improved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SIMON FORD,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>an angel looks on a madonna figure who is holding two children and being prayed to by 5 people</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Collins</hi> at the Kings Arms in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:2"/>
            <p>VIRO NATALIBUS, ERUDITIONE, Omnimodiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> VIRTUTIBUS Nobiliſſimo, <hi>GEORGIO</hi> Baroni de <hi>BERKELEY;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN ALBUM CURATORUM HONORIFICORUM HOSPITII Vulgo DICTI DE <hi>BRIDEWELL,</hi> Alteriúſque de <hi>BETHLEM,</hi> DEMISSIONE SUI GRATIOSA NUPER ADSCRIPTO;</p>
            <p>ET PROINDE IN HAC PAGELLA (HONORIS ergô) SEPARATIM NOMINANDO:</p>
            <p>HUNC (TANQUAM TESTI EXPERTO) De <hi>BEATIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DINE BENEFICENTIAE</hi> TRACTATULUM, Humillimè Offert, OMNI OBSERVANTIAE GENERE ADDICTISSIMUS,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIMON FORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL; Sir <hi>William Turner,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PRESIDENT, With his Aſſiſtants, the Governours of the two HOSPITALS of <hi>Bridewell</hi> and <hi>Bethlem.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IF, (as it hath of late in like caſes been cuſtomary) I ſhould plead the</hi> Authority <hi>of your</hi> Court, <hi>as that which hath without any</hi> inclination <hi>of mine own, ſolely prevailed with me to</hi> print <hi>this</hi> Diſcourſe; <hi>I muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſs, it would be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a modeſter kinde of diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation with you and the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For I muſt own, that when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the ſubſtance of it from the Pulpit in</hi> two Sermons <hi>(the one at</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49298:4"/> 
               <hi>the</hi> Spittle <hi>before the Lord Maior then being, and the Aldermen of this City, on</hi> Wedneſday <hi>in</hi> Eaſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>week, 1672. <hi>and the other, which was but the former (at the Inſtance of ſome of you) repeated with ſome ſuitable enlargements, in your own</hi> Chappel <hi>of</hi> Bridewell <hi>at your late General Meeting, 1673.) I was not without thoughts of publiſhing it: becauſe my principal Deſign in preaching it being (as in Duty I am bound, having by your favour been elected and hitherto continued</hi> Preacher <hi>to one of them) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the good of the</hi> two Hoſpitals <hi>under your Government; I juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the more publick I made it, the more effectually it was like to anſwer my end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Only I muſt withall acknowledge, that the general acceptance which it found from thoſe of you that heard me in</hi> both Auditories, <hi>and the testification of your Deſires (by an expreſs</hi> Order of Court) <hi>to have it printed, concurring with mine own</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49298:4"/> 
               <hi>inclinations; gave me a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional encouragement to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it thus to the publick View.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning the ſucceſs of which undertaking, I am not altogether out of hope that it may in ſome ſort anſwer my deſires; conſidering the</hi> ſerious Importance <hi>of the weighty</hi> Argument <hi>it handles, and the great ſuitableneſs of the matter contained in it, to the blowing up thoſe few ſparks of</hi> Charity, <hi>which (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe hard Times) remain yet unextinguiſhed in the breasts of many worthy Citizens and others; into ſuch Acts and Expreſſions, as the great</hi> Exigences <hi>of this</hi> City, <hi>and particularly, of theſe your</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals, <hi>do require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>However, if my hopes of ſucceſs upon others ſhould unhappily fail me; yet I have reaſon to believe that my Endeavours herein will meet with a favourable acceptance and compliance from you, who have already given me ſo great a pledge of it, in commanding its publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall not farther enlarge this</hi> Dedicatory Addreſs <hi>to you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſhall thereby the longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you from the Diſcourſe it ſelf; which I hope you had no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in calling for, than that you might read and practiſe it, and thereby acquire that</hi> Bleſſedneſs <hi>to your ſelves unto which it directs. Which alſo, that you may obtain, is and ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(Right Worſhipfull,)</salute>
               <signed>Your Obliged Servant in the Work of our Lord Jeſus, Simon Ford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49298:5"/>
            <head>The Bleſſedneſs of being Bountiful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Acts 20. 35.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>—It is more bleſſed to give than to receive.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1-50" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch hath always been the acknowledged Dominion of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbial Sayings</hi> over the Principles and Lives of mankind; that ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymologiſts have thence taken an Argument to derive the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> name of them from a Root which (though it have another ſignification beſides, yet) ſeems moſt of all to fit their purpoſe in that of <hi>ruling</hi> or <hi>commanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Dominion, (beſides what the worth and weight of their matter gives them) is in a great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49298:6"/> degree conferred upon them, by the great Reputation of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours; who (being ordinarily ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>wiſe,</hi> or <hi>great,</hi> or <hi>proſperous,</hi> beyond the rate of other men) contribute that veneration to their Speeches, which is wont to be given to their Perſons. Which veneration alſo they obtain the rather, becauſe they are looked on by Poſterity as the Abſtracts of thoſe grand Principles, by the Practice whereof thoſe eminent Perſons arrived at that degree of excellency in which they were placed; and are therefore eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt certain and compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious meaſures, by which the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all others can be governed, who deſign to arrive at the ſame degree of eminency by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
               <p>And hence (probably) it is, that the wiſdom of God thought meet to place a Book of ſuch Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the Canon of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with the great name of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49298:6"/> (who was moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently both <hi>wiſe,</hi> and <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>proſperous)</hi> prefixed; that the Principles of true Religion and Vertue, of which that Book is compoſed, might not be deſtitute even of that lower degree of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation (ſuperadded to their divine Authority) which reſults from the credit of humane Teſtimonials.</p>
               <p>To ſhorten this Preface: It is upon this account that I choſe at this time to ſpeak from this Text, which is much of the nature of a Proverbial Paradox, which not only contains in it a great Truth, and therein the moſt powerful motive to Works of Charity that can be couched in ſo few words; but is withall recommended from the excellency of its Authour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any of that kind. For ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing all thoſe that are digeſted into that one Book of Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture before mentioned to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally <hi>Solomon</hi>'s, (which yet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49298:7"/> ſome queſtion, and only entitle him to the collection of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of them;) yet, this <hi>Proverb</hi> is quoted from an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour in all the mentioned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, far beyond both him and all other men: one that was more truly than he, <hi>wiſer than all men;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King. 4. 31. 1 Cor. 1. 24.</note> for he was the <hi>wiſdom of God:</hi> one that was infinitely <hi>greater</hi> than he, or any other meer man; for he was <hi>the Power of God,</hi> and <note place="margin">Pſal. 72. 8, 9, 10.</note> of whoſe <hi>greatneſs</hi> even that of <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf was but a Type or ſhadow: and one that was alſo more <hi>proſperous</hi> than he, and all the moſt ſucceſsful men in the world; ſeeing the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign that ever was undertaken in the World (the redemption of mankind from all their greateſt, that is ſpiritual, dangers and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies) <hi>proſpered in his hand.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſ. 53. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For it is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf whom our Apoſtle (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing occaſion to make uſe of this Proverb, in his Viſitation Sermon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49298:7"/> to the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of which my Text is a part) avouches to be the utterer and frequent uſer of it. <hi>Ye ought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the words of the Lord Jeſus, how he ſaid</hi> (and it was his uſual ſaying, for ſo ſuch forms of quote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commonly import) that it is <hi>more bleſſed,</hi> or <hi>rather bleſſed,</hi> (for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> will bear both ſences) <hi>to give, than to receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though we read not this ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>in terminis,</hi> in any of the Goſpels of the Holy Evangeliſts who profeſſedly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook the penning of his Speeches and Actions; yet have we not therefore any ſufficient Reaſon to doubt the Truth of the Apoſtles Quotation; ſeeing it was not (as one of them profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for himſelf, and it is with the <note place="margin">John 20, 30, 31, 21, 25.</note> ſame reaſon to be ſo judged of all the reſt) the deſign of thoſe holy Penmen to give a perfect nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical account of every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Paſſage of our Saviours Life;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49298:8"/> but only to commend ſo much of it to Poſterity, as might (without tiring the Reader and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his memory with the length) ſuffice to beget a Faith that he was the Son of God, and to inſtruct him ſufficiently in thoſe Doctrines that were neceſſary to ſalvation. Yea, rather we have very weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſons to juſtifie the Apoſtle in this Quotation againſt all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is a ſaying, which doth ſo aptly ſute ſome others, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded from his mouth by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts; and which ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters mention, to ſalve In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters mention, to ſalve this Objection by Equivalency. For we find him in his firſt Sermon commending <hi>mercifulneſs</hi> to his Diſciples, under the ſame encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of <hi>Bleſſedneſs;</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 7.</note> in the account he gives them of the laſt Judgment, that he will then pronounce them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally <hi>bleſſed,</hi> who extend their bounty to him in his members;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49298:8"/> and thoſe <hi>eternally curſed,</hi> who have in ſuch good deeds been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly negligent and defective, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 34. to the end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe our Apoſtle quotes it before thoſe to whom the very form of his Speech ſuppoſeth it to be as well known as to himſelf; if not to ſome of them better, who (it may be) perſonally converſed with the Lord Jeſus, (which he himſelf did not) and heard it from his own lips. For he tells it them not as a new thing that they knew not before, but onely bids them remember it; intimating that their own memories could not but atteſt that it was his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to whom he attributed it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Add we to this Evidence, that the natural import of the Doctrine herein contained is ſuch, that it cannot with like <hi>Decorum</hi> be aſcribed to any man, as to him, who was himſelf (electively) the <hi>greatest Giver,</hi> and the <hi>least Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver</hi> that ever was in this world;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49298:9"/> and one (therefore) who muſt be ſuppoſed to have moſt amply ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> it ſpeaks of, by the conſtant practice of it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Mind we, <hi>laſtly,</hi> that the <hi>Saying</hi> it ſelf is a moſt <hi>divine ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> every way beſitting that mouth which ſpake the very thoughts of <hi>God's boſome</hi> to men; <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 18.</note> ſeeing it ſo aptly and adequately expreſſeth the very inward ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſatisfactions of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence, which imploys it ſelf inceſſantly in being the inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible Fountain of <hi>all good</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>givings</hi> and <hi>perfect gifts</hi> to his Creatures, upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (as you will ſee more fully anon) but only the pleaſure he takes therein.</p>
               <p>You ſee, by this time (belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) a double motive to engage your attention, to what I have to ſay to you on this Text: the <hi>great Authority</hi> by which it comes recommended; and the <hi>great</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49298:9"/> 
                  <hi>Truth</hi> contained in it. Which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention ſo prepared, I ſhall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, by handling it in this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. I ſhall <hi>open</hi> the words by a brief <hi>Explication.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Shew you the <hi>Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Reaſon</hi> upon which the great Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them ſtands.</item>
                  <item>3. Gather ſome <hi>practical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> from it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I. In the <hi>Explication</hi> of the Words, I have promiſed to be brief. And therefore I ſhall wave the Philoſophical Notions in a great meaſure, which (being in general conſidered without the coherence in which here they ſtand) they would afford; as, concerning [The nature, and kinds, and degrees of humane Bleſſedneſs; and (that which might in ſome ſort alſo conduce to our preſent purpoſe) the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral tendency of Acts of <hi>giving</hi> beyond thoſe of <hi>receiving</hi> to that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49298:10"/> 
                  <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> naturally conſidered:] as apprehending, partly, that thoſe notions are not much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to your Chriſtian Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and partly, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and our Apoſtle quoting this ſaying from him, cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to intend the inſtruction of their Hearers in a <hi>Metaphyſical Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation;</hi> but rather, the laying before them and us a <hi>moral dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> to teach us by what acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this life men may moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the advancement of their own felicity.</p>
               <p>And ſo the words are a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of our Saviour upon a ſuppoſed Queſtion concerning the comparative Acts of <hi>Giving</hi> and <hi>Receiving</hi> the good things of this Life: to wit [<hi>which of the two doth moſt truely and moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully conduce to man's bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi>] In which Determination he caſts the ſcale on the ſide of <hi>Giving,</hi> (which imports, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, the doing good to others
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49298:10"/> in whatever kind or way, and in ſpecial, by Acts of Liberality and Bounty;) againſt <hi>Receiving,</hi> (which, in general, includes whatever way of doing good to a man's ſelf in this life, and in ſpecial, by Acts of getting and keeping this World's goods to his own ſingle emolument and advantage) as tending to make him more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and cumulatively bleſſed. For in this ſence, it is plain by the Context, this Proverb of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is here made uſe of by the Apoſtle, as an Argument to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to <hi>preach the Goſpel</hi> to their people in their preſent ſtate of affairs, <hi>gratis,</hi> and therein to <hi>give</hi> them that temporal reward in to the bargain, which they might (as he elſewhere determines, <hi>viz. 1 Cor.</hi> 9. 12.) have challenged of them, together with the Goſpel; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much a <hi>gift</hi> to forgive a Debt, as to <hi>give</hi> a ſumm of money out of ones own Purſe: which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49298:11"/> piece of bountiful ſelf-denyal he exhorts them to for this end, that they might (for their more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual edification) comply with the weakneſs of their young converts who loved not (as few do) a <hi>chargeable Goſpel;</hi> though they were thereby forced in the mean while, as he himſelf did, to <hi>labour with their own hands</hi> to get a livelihood. And this is that, which in the beginning of this Verſe, he calls, <hi>[ſupporting the weak;]</hi> to induce them where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, he quotes this notable <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> to aſſure them that the inward ſatisfaction which they would receive from the conſcience of having faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promoted the ſalvation of ſouls by preaching under ſuch diſadvantageous circumſtances, would be of more worth to them, than the richeſt temporal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Revenues they could expect, or might lawfully chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, for their pains.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49298:11"/>
               <p>So that (in ſumm) you may take the whole ſence of the words in this ſhort Paraphraſe. Q. d. <hi>I know the World is generally apt to think that the way to Happineſs is by getting and poſſeſſing abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of earthly goods. But I tell you from the Lord Jeſus, that man provides more truly and effectually for his own bleſſedneſs, and promotes it more plentifully, by contributing to the benefiting of others, then by doing good to himſelf: he is a ſurer and a greater gainer by giving, then by having; by laying out thus, then by laying up, as the most of the World do; by Bounty and Charity, then by Covetouſneſs and Parſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>II. And this <hi>Paradox</hi> (for ſuch it ſeems to all Worldlings) thus explained, I am (in the next place) engaged to make good from its proper foundations of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For though ſpeaking to an Auditory of profeſſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as I do, I might very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49298:12"/> in the great Authority of our Saviour, to which we all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, as a ſufficient juſtification of that which is his own Aſſertion: Yet, becauſe the greateſt divine Truths carry greater Evidence with them when they are proved to be conſonant to the common Notions implanted in humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; I therefore think it needful to fortifie this Doctrine (abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly capable of it) with Proofs of that kind alſo.</p>
               <p>And this undertaking I thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perform. All the good things which generally (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the opinion of worldlings) are thought contributary to <hi>ſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,</hi> are either <hi>honourable, pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> or <hi>profitable:</hi> and (if this be granted, which I know none that denies,) I muſt confeſs my ſelf much out of the way in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Reaſon and Argument, if I be not able to make it good, that <hi>Giving</hi> hath more of all theſe in it, than <hi>Receiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49298:12"/>
               <p>[1. Begin we therefore with the greater <hi>Honourableneſs</hi> of Bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Honour</hi> is the real inward eſteem that Perſons who are meet Judges therein have of any one for things and actions of true worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency. So that, to be truly <hi>Honourable,</hi> is, to be and do that which is <hi>really worthy</hi> and <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;</hi> and which is ſo eſteemed to be by the moſt <hi>competent Judges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence I have <hi>two things</hi> on this Head to prove.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That <hi>Acts of giving</hi> are Acts of more <hi>real worth</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> than thoſe of <hi>receiving.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That they are, and have always been <hi>ſo eſteemed</hi> by the moſt <hi>competent Judges,</hi> and ſuch as in this caſe can rationally be refuſed by no man.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1.] There is a <hi>real worth</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> in Acts of <hi>Giving,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond thoſe of <hi>Receiving.</hi> Which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49298:13"/> is to me evident from <hi>two</hi> main Arguments.</p>
               <p>(1. From the greater confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which the <hi>former</hi> bear to the genuine temper and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Soul of Man. The ſtrength of which Argument lies in this Principle; That where any Nature is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in it ſelf to be Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, (as certainly humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is, being, in the confeſſion of Heathens themſelves, <hi>God's off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17. 23.</note> in a ſpecial way of Deſcent, and ſtanding not ſo many removes from him, as all other ſublunary natures do;) there it is moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable for all that partake of that Nature to act conformably thereunto. Now the humane Soul is certainly a Being endowed with large, generous, and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent propenſions: ſo that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without very great uneaſineſs be confined and cooped up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in narrow and ſelfiſh Principles. It is ſtrongly inclined to be ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49298:13"/> and converſive; to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative and obliging; to be pitiful and compaſſionate; all which qualities are of a <hi>giving</hi> nature: and that to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the expreſſions of theſe inclinations by one man to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are ordinarily called (as if they only were ſo, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary propenſions were account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an implicite abrenunciation of humane nature, and an herd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ones ſelf with Brutes,) by the name of <hi>Humanity.</hi> Inſomuch that our Saviour, when he was to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake an Office for our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which required compaſſionate affections, choſe to be <hi>made like unto us in all things,</hi> that he might, (by the inclinations of his own aſſumed humane nature, as well as by the determinations of his Divine Will,) become a <hi>Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 17. 4. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>compaſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched with the feeling of our infirmities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Adde we, (for a cloſe of this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49298:14"/> Head) to this evidence of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> one or two from <hi>Experience;</hi> which, where it is conſtant, is wont to found Maxims and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for the uſe of Reaſon it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> Inſtance I ſhall give, ſhall be in <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> wherein the ſoul of man doth moſt voluntarily fling off all diſguiſes, and appears moſt delightfully in its proper Naturals to the object of its dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Affections. Now in ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances wherein uſually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts of friendſhip do ariſe, the great diſpute betwixt thoſe Souls that are ſo linked together, is, whether the one or the other ſhall exceed in acts of noble and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous bounty: which extends to a pulling down all the Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> and rendring all things, even life it ſelf, mutually <hi>common.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>other</hi> Inſtance ſhall be in a <hi>Vice,</hi> which (even in thoſe who at other times uſe all the Arts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49298:14"/> they can to diſguiſe their natures, and keep their breaſts ſhut to all mankinde,) is wont to pick the lock of mens boſoms, and, whether they will or no, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to common view: I mean, that of <hi>Dunkenneſs.</hi> Now in that ſinfull exceſs, among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vicious inclinations (which are various in ſeveral men, and which then appear variouſly,) this one vertuous propenſion, (which that vice that moſt trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms men to beaſts, cannot era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate) doth moſt evidently and almoſt univerſally diſcover it ſelf; inſomuch that the moſt covetous and illiberal Perſons in the world are in their <hi>cups</hi> alwayes gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly frolick, and free of their Purſes; and thoſe that can worſt ſpare it many times, are yet apt to take it ill that any one in the company offers to pay any part of the reckoning but themſelves.</p>
               <p>Which I make uſe of only, as an argument of great force from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49298:15"/> common experience, that the purely Natural Temper of the Humane Soul is more inclined to <hi>Giving</hi> than <hi>Receiving;</hi> and (by conſequence) that that Propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which is thus naturally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in us, renders thoſe Acts which are moſt couformable to it <hi>(viz.</hi> thoſe of <hi>Giving,)</hi> moſt <hi>Honourable.</hi> My <hi>firſt</hi> proof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecond,</hi> I ſhall take from the greater agreeableneſs of Acts of <hi>Giving</hi> to principles of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> than thoſe of <hi>Receiving.</hi> Which if I can make good, I doubt not of gaining what I intend by it. Now this Notion I thus make out.</p>
               <p>God hath originally, by the Law of the Creation, <hi>given the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 115. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Earth to the Children of men:</hi> that is, hath entituled every man to ſo much of it, as may yield him a competent and comfortable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence. And the propriety that one man hath in this, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that proportion of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49298:15"/> common Fathers Bounty, is not ſet out by him, immediately; but by particular Compacts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of men themſelves. Which Compacts and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, though they be ſufficient barres, (even upon the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Conſcience) to fence mens particular rights againſt the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of fraud or violence, to alter the poſſeſſion againſt the owners will; yet cannot deſtroy the fundamental Title that any man in want hath to be ſupplyed in his neceſſities, ſutably to his occaſions, out of the abundance of other men. Whence it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows, that there lies an obligation of Juſtice upon the abounding poſſeſſor of this worlds goods, in all ſuch caſes, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in all other, wherein any of thoſe uſes are concerned, which God and Nature have made ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the ſupport of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Humanity in the ſeveral ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of the World) to quit
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49298:16"/> his propriety ſo far, by his own conſent, as may ſuffice for the relief of his <hi>Brethren,</hi> and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of thoſe uſes, (whatever they be,) without which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde cannot be preſerved or maintained as it ought to be.</p>
               <p>Which is the Reaſon, in likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, why the abundance of any mans Riches is called by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>that which is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>anothers, (i. e.</hi> anothers with him, and not entirely his <hi>own:)</hi> ſo that no man can juſtly ſay of his worldly Eſtate, as <hi>Nabal</hi> did, and in his ſenſe, <hi>[My bread, and my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>water, and my fleſh,</hi> &amp;c.] as if no creature had any ſhare therein but himſelf. For indeed, (beſides that all we have, even whiles we have it, is (in reference to <hi>God)</hi> not <hi>ours;</hi> for he loſeth not his Supreme Right and Propriety of Dominion by any of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:) a greater part of moſt mens Eſtates than uſually they imagine, is by the Original Divine Law
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49298:16"/> that I told you of before, not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely their <hi>own,</hi> even with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their <hi>brethren</hi> in huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but they, in ſeveral capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, may juſtly challenge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſhares therein, which cannot with Juſtice be denyed them. And particularly, in the caſe of Charity (which I ſpecially here drive at,) <hi>Almes</hi> is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore frequently called <hi>Justice</hi> or <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and he that gives them, a <hi>Juſt</hi> or <hi>Righteous</hi> man, in the uſual Hebrew Idiom through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Scriptures of the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> and ſome ſay, in the <hi>New</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 1. 2 Cor. 9. 10, &amp;c.</note> alſo in ſome places of ſpecial note, which I will not now inſiſt on. And he that denyes or delayes his relief, in his <hi>Brothers</hi> needs, is ſaid (by <hi>Solomon)</hi> to <hi>withhold</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>good from thoſe to whom it is due,</hi> or (as the Margin reads it) <hi>from the Owners thereof.</hi> So that (Juſtice, which is the foundation of all moral vertues, being on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Honourable, and Bounty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49298:17"/> an Act of Juſtice; and tenaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or ſordid parſimony, on the contrary, of injuſtice;) it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that that <hi>act</hi> which bears moſt conformity to Juſtice, muſt be more Honourable than that which for a great part is, and more commonly is ſuſpected to be, of Confederacy with Injuſtice: <hi>i. e. Giving,</hi> then <hi>Receiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2.] And leſt any perſon ſhould ſeek protection from the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Reflexions this Doctrine makes upon his ſordidneſs; by alledging, that this Judgement, concerning the real excellency of acts of <hi>Giving</hi> above <hi>Receiving,</hi> is not made by <hi>competent Judges;</hi> I ſhall (in the next place) ſhew you who they are on whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations I rely, for the juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying this Aſſertion: who (I am bold to aſſert) are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed (by any perſon who owns himſelf a <hi>Creature,</hi> a <hi>Man,</hi> or a <hi>Chriſtian,)</hi> as the moſt meet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in this matter.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49298:17"/>
               <p>(1. The <hi>first Judge</hi> to whom I appeal in this cauſe, is <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who muſt needs be owned by every <hi>Creature,</hi> as the <hi>Supreme Judge</hi> in a Court of <hi>Honour;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt excellent of Beings, and the Fountain of all that is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. Now <hi>God,</hi> beſides what he hath declared in his written word, which tells us that the <hi>horn</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112. 9.</note> of him that <hi>diſperſeth and giveth to the poor ſhall be exalted,</hi> (a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor taken from thoſe ruling Beaſts in the Herd that carry their <hi>horns higher</hi> than the reſt, with a kinde of glorying, and confidence,) <hi>with honour:</hi> I ſay, beſides what his Word, (in that and other places) declares ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely; God doth moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently pronounce his <hi>Judgement</hi> in this matter, by his own acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; who, (renouncing the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of <hi>receiving</hi> from any other Being, as a <hi>diſparagement,)</hi> takes it for his <hi>honour</hi> to be and to be owned as the univerſal <hi>Giver,</hi> that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49298:18"/> 
                  <hi>gives to all life and breath and all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> 
                  <hi>things:</hi> and argues, (with ſome kinde of exprobration) the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs of thoſe mens thoughts concerning him, that conceit any man can <hi>give</hi> any thing to him; from the <hi>precedency</hi> and cauſality of his Bounty to all that capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we can pretend to, to do any thing to oblige him withall, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>of him and through him</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 35, 37.</note> 
                  <hi>are all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(2. Nor can the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> be refuſed as a <hi>competent Judge</hi> in this matter, by any that owns the Name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the higheſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the whole Creation to be due to him; who is <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by all the Angels of God, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 6. Phil. 2. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>hatha Name above every Name, a Name to which every knee muſt bow,</hi> &amp;c. Now it muſt needs be yielded by any rational man, that (had he not, as he hath, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bally declared his Judgement in this particular of <hi>Bleſsedneſs</hi> as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49298:18"/> well in many other Scriptures, as in the Text, yet) he hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently by his deeds proclaimed that to be the moſt <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>honourable</hi> action, by the conſtant exerciſe whereof he procured his <hi>own Honours; emptying</hi> himſelf that he might <hi>fill us:</hi> and <hi>becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poor for our ſakes that we</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 7. 2. Cor. 8. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>through his poverty might be rich;</hi> and in the proſpect whereof, he quitted the <hi>natural Honour</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>equal to his Father,</hi> to aſſume an office wherein he was to be his <hi>Inferiour,</hi> that he might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by acquire the <hi>peculiar Honour</hi> of being our <hi>Redeemer.</hi> Now it is evident, that the whole work of our Redemption conſiſted of acts of <hi>Giving,</hi> not <hi>Receiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(3. However, as <hi>Men,</hi> it is to be hoped that none that owns himſelf of that number, will in this matter refuſe the <hi>Judgement of all mankinde.</hi> Which Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be evidently gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49298:19"/>
               <p>(1.) From the reſpect and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which (all the world over) ſuperiour Relations expect and receive from their Inferiours, which in humanity are equal to themſelves: whereof, if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Reaſon, there can be no other given (antecedent to Divine or Humane Laws, which yet are founded upon antecedent Reaſon) than this; that they are, or elſe are ſuppoſed to be, the Authors of ſuch and ſuch bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits (either of Being, or conducing to well-being) which thoſe Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours receive from them, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy under them.</p>
               <p>(2.) From the Teſtimonies of Gratitude, which are every where and in all Ages given to thoſe who are eminently beneficial to Mankinde, or to particular Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men. Wherein, there could never be ſo univerſal a conſent, but from the concurrence of all mens Judgements in this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that <hi>to do good, is more noble than to receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49298:19"/>
               <p>Now this is evident, (in matter of fact) from all Hiſtories. The old Heathens thought they could not honour ſuch Inſtruments ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently with any humane Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; and therefore they dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, (as far as in them lay, by Temples, and Altars, and Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> the Inventours of uſefull Arts and Sciences; the Founders of Kingdoms and Empires; the Authours of publick Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Laws; and the great and noted Champions and defenders, or Saviours and deliverers, of any Communities of men from great and publick calamities.</p>
               <p>Yea, they beſtowed like Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, upon the Heavenly Bodies, and Earthly Elements. The Sun and the Moon, and divers of the noted Stars: yea the Earth it ſelf, and the Sea that encompaſſeth it, the Fire and the Aire, and Rivers and Springs; (and whatever elſe contributed to the ſupport of man;) were either reputed Gods
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49298:20"/> themſelves, or the ſpecial reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies of ſome Deities, who by them communicated their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Bounties to mankinde.</p>
               <p>And where theſe Heathen Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries have been exploded, yet even there, men have generally thought ſuch perſons worthy the higheſt Acknowledgements that Humane Nature was capable of: Which they have expreſſed in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyricks and Poems, in Statues and other magnificent Structures, in Coyns and other publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, (and whatever other laſting Monuments they could deviſe;) to render them, as to their Names and Memories (who could not be in their Bodies) immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</p>
               <p>Let now, (for a cloſe of this Head) the ſordid ſelf-ended ſort of men, ſhew us any Inſtances, if they can, of like Honours done to thoſe who (without doing good to any but themſelves) have ſpent their Time in <hi>finding riches</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49298:20"/> 
                  <hi>as a neſt, and gathering them like</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 10. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>eggs,</hi> to ſit on. Yea, rather, let the experience of all Ages ſpeak, and it will tell us, that there are no ſort of men in the world, whom the generality of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde have treated with more curſes and bitter ſcoffs whiles they lived; or hiſſed off the ſtage of this life with more open re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and infamy when they died. So that I hope, I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently demonſtrated, that (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we reſpect the nature of the Acts themſelves, or the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgement of God and Man,) <hi>it is more honourable</hi> by far <hi>to give than to receive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[2. The <hi>Pleaſure</hi> which accrews to men from Acts of Bounty, doth no leſs exceed that which ariſeth from thoſe of Covetouſneſs and Parſimony.</p>
               <p>Of which there needs no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evidence (in Reaſon) than what I before intimated upon the <hi>former Head; viz.</hi> [the greater
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49298:21"/> 
                  <hi>agreeableneſs</hi> of ſuch actions to the <hi>native largeneſs</hi> and <hi>generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the <hi>ſoul</hi> of man, and the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Juſtice:]</hi> There being no ſuch ſatisfactory pleaſure in the world attainable by Humane Nature, as is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward content which a vertuous man takes in reflecting upon thoſe things which he hath done with the approbation of his own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Conſcience; and no greater grief, than when they complain that they are violenced and oppreſſed by unnatural and unreaſonable Luſts and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>But to make this alſo more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by particular Inſtances.</p>
               <p>(1. It is an undenyable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Pleaſure that <hi>Giving</hi> yields beyond <hi>Receiving,</hi> that God, whoſe infinite Perfection placeth him beyond all capacity of <hi>Receiving</hi> (as was ſaid before) can be ſuppoſed to have no other motive to <hi>Give,</hi> as he doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49298:21"/> but the inward ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he findes in Beneficence it ſelf. Whence ſome tell us, that his Name, <hi>El-ſhaddai,</hi> hath the Notion of a <hi>full breaſt</hi> in it, to which nothing can be ſo pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as to vent it ſelf into the mouth of the ſucking Infant: which is pained with its own fulneſs, and findes its only eaſe in being emptied. And indeed, the complacency that he is ſaid to have taken in all the works of his Creation, when he had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them, implyed in that ſo often repeated Phraſe, <hi>God ſaw</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 10, 12, 18, 21, 25, 31. Pſal. 145. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>that it was good;</hi> the readineſs that is in him to <hi>ſatisfie the deſires of every living thing;</hi> the conſtant unweariedneſs of his Bounty (the greateſt evidence of the pleaſure taken in any action) <hi>continually</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 104. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>filling the earth with his riches;</hi> the invitations he ſo frequently <note place="margin">Pſ. 50. 15.</note> gives to men to <hi>call upon him, opening the mouths</hi> of their holy deſires <hi>wide</hi> that he may <hi>fill them,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 81. 10.</note>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49298:22"/> and <hi>in all things making their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>known to him;</hi> with the <hi>delight</hi> he profeſſeth to take in <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 8.</note> the <hi>prayers</hi> of good men, which invite his Bounties: ſufficiently argue the <hi>divine pleaſure</hi> that is in <hi>giving;</hi> being the ſatisfaction which God himſelf chooſeth for himſelf. And to be ſure, be the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of <hi>receiving</hi> what it will, it cannot pretend to ſo high an Original.</p>
               <p>(2. The like may (ſecondly) be argued from the example of our Lord Jeſus, who ſeems by his actions to have preferred the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of <hi>ſeeing</hi> his <hi>ſpiritual ſeed,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 10. Heb. 2. 10. 5. 9.</note> and <hi>bringing many ſons to glory,</hi> by being <hi>the Author and Captain of their Salvation;</hi> before the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſatisfactions and delights of his <hi>Fathers Boſom, wherein he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 8. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>alwayes before him</hi> from all eternity: and that ſo far, that he deprived himſelf (in a ſort) of the very pleaſures of Divinity for a Time, by becoming Man,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49298:22"/> that he might be the Redeemer and Saviour of Mankinde.</p>
               <p>The very <hi>proſpect</hi> of this great work cheered his heart before he undertook it, he <hi>rejoyced in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 8. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>habitable part of Gods Earth, and his delights were with the Sons of men;</hi> when he entred upon that <hi>Body</hi> the Father had <hi>prepared</hi> for him, though he knew he was to make it a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> yet he did it (as he profeſſeth) with <hi>delight to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 5, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>do his Fathers will</hi> therein; he ſpent all his Time on Earth in <hi>going about and doing good gratis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 10. 38.</note> to thoſe miſerable Creatures that could not any way requite him; did divers of his great works in <note place="margin">Joh. 7. 4, 5.</note> ſilence and privacy, and forbad <note place="margin">Luk. 5. 14. 8. 56. Joh. 6. 15.</note> the publication of them; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the Honours that men offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for thoſe that were of too publick benefit to be concealed; and when he knew that his dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Hour was come,</hi> how did he complain the minutes moved ſlowly, till he had opportunity
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49298:23"/> offered to accompliſh that <hi>bloody</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 50.</note> 
                  <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> that he foretold he was to be <hi>baptized withall?</hi> His Croſs on which he ſuffered, he is ſaid <note place="margin">Col. 2. 15.</note> to <hi>triumph</hi> upon, as a Conquerour in a Chariot of State. And (after his Death,) his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion into Heaven again, he looked on as a <hi>Joy ſet before him;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 2.</note> not ſurely <hi>on his own account</hi> only, but becauſe he alſo knew he was <hi>going</hi> to <hi>prepare Manſions</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 2.</note> for us, as our <hi>Harbinger,</hi> to lead us the way into the <hi>Holy Place,</hi> as our <hi>forerunner,</hi> and to lie as our <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Lieger</hi> there to do us good Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by his <hi>interceſſion</hi> till he had <hi>ſaved us to the utmoſt.</hi> So that our <note place="margin">7. 25.</note> Saviours <hi>Practice</hi> is a full and further evidence of the <hi>Pleaſure</hi> that is in <hi>Giving</hi> more than <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(3. Gods holy Angels, as (of all Creatures) they neareſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Divine Nature, ſo herein they proportionably imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his perfections; that (like
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49298:23"/> him) they are continually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in doing good upon the like motives of the delight and ſatisfaction they finde therein. For continuing in the ſtate of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity wherein they were at firſt created, they muſt be ſuppoſed to be above any need of <hi>receiving</hi> any reall addition to the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which the continual <hi>ſtanding in Gods preſence</hi> affords them; and yet, with what cheerfulneſs and alacrity do they <hi>doe the will of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>God,</hi> even in thoſe <hi>low Miniſteries</hi> whereunto they ſtoop to ſerve our occaſions? They <hi>keep us in all our wayes,</hi> and that with as much carefulneſs, as the Nurſe doth the tender Infant, <hi>bearing us</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 91. 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>up in their hands,</hi> that we <hi>daſh not ſo much as our foot againſt a ſtone;</hi> they <hi>pitch their tents,</hi> as a <note place="margin">Pſ. 34. 7.</note> conſtant life-guard, about good men, (yea, an whole Army of <note place="margin">2 Kings 6. 17.</note> them, ſometimes, about one Saint) for their ſecurity; they <hi>fight</hi> for us againſt evil Spirits, under the <note place="margin">Apoc. 12. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49298:24"/> Captain of our Salvation; they <hi>fly ſwiftly,</hi> as our Intelligencers, <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 21.</note> on good errands, to comfort us; and theſe, and all other good offices, they are ready to do on all occaſions, for the leaſt and meaneſt of Mankinde (even thoſe <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 7. Mat. 18. 10.</note> whom we, who are their <hi>own fleſh,</hi> are apt to <hi>deſpiſe)</hi> while they <hi>live;</hi> and when they <hi>die,</hi> think it not beneath them to take up their <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 32.</note> Souls into their bleſſed Arms, and carry them to their habitation of <hi>bliſse</hi> and glory. All which offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they would never deſcend to do with ſo much unwearied ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity, if they found not the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them pleaſurable: for if they diſguſted them in any ſort, as burdenſome and uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble employments; it muſt needs imply, that all the while they are ſo employed, their <hi>perfect holineſs</hi> muſt ſuffer a diminution, and their <hi>perfect happineſs</hi> an eclipſe.</p>
               <p>(4. But all theſe Inſtances, it may be objected, are <hi>above</hi> us,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49298:24"/> and ſo not imitable by us: nor are our pleaſures to be meaſured by theirs. Let us therefore (in the <hi>next</hi> place) make triall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even <hi>men of like paſſions with our ſelves,</hi> have not been wont to finde the ſame ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>giving;</hi> and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon preferred it before <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(1.) Look we firſt, on the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian part of Mankinde. And, whatever we may obſerve in the later Ages and very dreggs of Chriſtianity, whrein Religion is even ſwallowed up and devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Intereſt all the world over; yet I am ſure, <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> Thoſe firſt Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our Maſter Chriſt took the greateſt delight in copying out the great examples of his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity and Bounty: They ſold (ſome of them) conſiderable Eſtates, and gave in the <hi>price of them</hi> to the common ſtock, to ſupply the neceſſary charges of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49298:25"/> the firſt Plantation of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Acts.</hi> 4. 34. to the end. They carryed about the great and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable riches of Chriſt,</hi> and <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 14.</note> ſcattered the <hi>ſavour of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> with <hi>triumph in every place</hi> freely: and when they might, refuſed to <hi>receive</hi> any thing from thoſe to whom they <hi>gave</hi> ſo much, and would not be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of this <hi>glorying,</hi> nor ſuffer it <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 15.</note> to be <hi>made voyd:</hi> accounting it the very <hi>reward</hi> of their work to do it <hi>without reward;</hi> and render <note place="margin">V. 18.</note> the Goſpel <hi>without charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the great hardſhips and hazards that they underwent, in the Diſcharge of this Duty ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely beneficial to Mankinde, they did undergoe with the greateſt delight and inward ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. <hi>I take pleaſure</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>in infirmities, (i. e.</hi> of ſuffering) <hi>in reproaches, in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>in perſecutions, in distreſſes for Christs ſake:</hi> which abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſhews what <hi>pleaſure</hi> that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49298:25"/> work yielded, that made all thoſe neceſſary difficulties <hi>pleaſurable,</hi> which were then to be encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for its ſake. For, however they that underwent theſe things had by Faith a proſpect of a <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture great reward,</hi> which contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted very much to their preſent Comfort; yet, even that argues ſufficiently the verity of our Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, that in that condition wherein they were not in any temporal reſpect <hi>receivers,</hi> nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being ſo, they found ſuch over-ballancing pleaſures in the nature and conſequences of their very work, as weighed down all the diſcouraging Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in which they were by Providence engaged.</p>
               <p>(2.) But, to be ſure, whatever future hopes <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had to encourage them in well doing with delight: the <hi>Heathens</hi> had none ſuch; for the Apoſtle tells <note place="margin">Eph. 2 12. 1 Theſſ. 4. 13.</note> us, they were <hi>without hope (i. e.</hi> ſuch as is grounded and certain,)
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49298:26"/> of theſe felicities of another world. And yet even divers of them, have found a kinde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual Epicuriſme (if I may ſo ſay) in the very acts of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence. Of which it is a notable Inſtance which <hi>Xenophon</hi> gives us in the character of his Heroe, of whom he tells us moſt divinely, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he had a greater delight in what he gave than in what he poſſeſsed.</hi> And on the other ſide, it is a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſelf-diſpleaſure of a vertuous man, when he hath miſſed the opportunity of doing good in this kinde; that the good Emperour <hi>Titus</hi> was wont to complain he had <hi>loſt that day,</hi> which he had ſpent without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome body a good Turn; than which, nothing can more ſtrongly argue the pleaſure he found in every <hi>other Day</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had been ſo imployed.</p>
               <p>(3.) Laſtly, look we on <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde indefinitely,</hi> and we ſhall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49298:26"/> finde, that all perſons (whether Chriſtians or Heathens) own a great Pleaſure in <hi>giving</hi> or <hi>doing</hi> good to others, beyond the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of what <hi>receiving</hi> or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to themſelves yields. For whence is it elſe, that the carefull Nurſe delightfully ſuffers her body to be drained of the beſt nouriſhment it receives, in ſuckling her Infant; that ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoes with ſinging ſo many nauſeous drudgeries for him; and diſquiets her ſelf with ſo many reſtleſs and wakefull nights to breed him; from whom for divers months ſhe can expect no other preſent return than a few ſmiles now and then, when ſhe can get him in a good humour; and whoſe future qualities or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſhe cannot foreſee ſo as to expect any certain future requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal from him? Whence is it, that every one generally loves the <hi>creature</hi> of his <hi>own Bounty,</hi> and ſtudies to oblige him more, to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49298:27"/> whom he hath formerly been wonted to ſhew ſpecial kindneſſes? And yet this many times is done to thoſe that have nothing of real worth to deſerve, nor ever arrive at proportionable capacities to requite them. Certainly, the moſt obvious Reaſon of theſe actions, that occurres to a conſidering man, muſt be (that that I am diſcourſing of,) that to all ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Beings there is a <hi>pleaſure</hi> that accompanies <hi>giving</hi> or Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in any kinde; which is more generous and refined than any that comes in by <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(5. Laſtly, it ſeems not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unworthy to be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of upon this Head, that the Scripture (in conformity with this Notion of <hi>the pleaſure of Giving,</hi> and probably the more to commend it to us to make an experiment in our ſelves) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the inanimate Creatures themſelves as Inſtances of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49298:27"/> in acts of beneficence to Mankinde.</p>
               <p>For thus the <hi>outgoings of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 65. 8:</note> 
                  <hi>Morning and Evening are ſaid to rejoyce,</hi> when in their conſtant vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes they refreſh us: thus the <hi>Sun,</hi> when he ariſeth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the world, is deſcribed as a <hi>Bridegroom coming out of his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 19. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Chamber, and a Giant rejoycing to run his race:</hi> thus, in <hi>Jothams</hi> Parable, the <hi>Olive,</hi> and the <hi>Vine,</hi> and the <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> are repreſented as unwilling to forgoe the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of bearing ſweet fruit to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>divine Sacrifices, and humane Treatments, to obtain a Monarchy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 9. 9, 11, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>among the Trees:</hi> and thus, laſtly, the <hi>Paſtures,</hi> when they are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Graſs, and <hi>Flocks</hi> to <note place="margin">Pſ. 65. 13.</note> crop it, and the <hi>Valleys,</hi> when <hi>laden with Corn</hi> to be reaped by us, are ſaid to <hi>ſhout</hi> and ſing for joy. As, on the other ſide, the <hi>Heavens</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>black</hi> with <note place="margin">Jer. 4. 28. 12. 4. Iſ. 24. 4, 7. 33. 9.</note> grief, and the <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>mourn,</hi> and the <hi>Vine to languiſh</hi> (as it were)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49298:28"/> with ſorrow; when in a barren year their wonted fertility is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained.</p>
               <p>In ſumme therefore, (to cloſe up this head too) whether we take meaſure of the delight and pleaſantneſs that is in Acts of <hi>Giving</hi> beyond <hi>Receiving;</hi> either from <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or good <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> or <hi>inanimate Creatures</hi> themſelves, (which diſtribution takes in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Beings but Devils, whoſe delight, indeed, is only in doing miſchief:) we finde, that the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity that accrews from <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> is greater from <hi>giving</hi> than <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[3. The <hi>third</hi> and <hi>laſt thing</hi> that contributes to <hi>bleſsedneſs</hi> is <hi>Profit.</hi> And my next buſineſs is to ſhew, that in that reſpect alſo <hi>Giving</hi> hath the advantage of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,</hi> as being of the two the more <hi>profitable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo it is both in reference to the Benefit that thereby is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49298:28"/> in <hi>this World,</hi> and in that which <hi>is to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(1. In reference to <hi>this World,</hi> There is a threefold Concern to be regarded, wherein the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage I ſpeak of evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Life.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In Sickneſs and Death.</p>
               <p n="3">3. After Death.</p>
               <p>1.) In <hi>Life,</hi> (this Life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">Pſ. 17. 14.</note> the Worldlings <hi>portion</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally lies) mans portion of this Worlds good things is by acts of <hi>Bounty,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Beſt Secured,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Moſt Comfortably enjoy'd,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Moſt plentifully Improved.</p>
               <p>(1.) This Portion is hereby <hi>beſt ſecured.</hi> Inſomuch, that no Deeds or Evidences, or Bonds or Mortgages, or Baggs or Cheſts, or Walls or Forts, or Locks or Barres, or Bolts or Guards, afford us like Security for what we have; as <hi>charitable Giving</hi> beſtows upon us. And that, not only in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49298:29"/> to a <hi>Security</hi> of <hi>Equivalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> (in which notion St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> handſomly Rhetoricates with the rich man in the Goſpel, who was ſollicitous to <hi>pull down</hi> his <hi>old</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 12. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Barns,</hi> as not big enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his increaſe, and <hi>build big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> when he tells him, that the courſe he took was the way to <hi>pull down</hi> rather than to <hi>build;</hi> and addes, that he will direct him to a better courſe to ſecure and lay up his Goods, by making the <hi>houſes of the Widows, the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs of the Poor, and the Mouths of the Orphans his Barns and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries;</hi> And our Saviour before him, when he tells us of <hi>laying</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>up our Treaſure</hi> (by laying it out,) where <hi>ruſt or moth doth not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt,</hi> and <hi>where thieves cannot break through and ſteal;</hi> and to put our money into <hi>baggs that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 12. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>will not wax old,</hi> &amp;c:) but alſo in reference to that <hi>temporal Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in kinde, which the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling moſt looks after, in whoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49298:29"/> Hearts as well as in his Deeds <hi>[to have and to hold]</hi> is the clauſe of principal reſpect and eſteem. Let us ſee therefore, how even this Security may be chiefly attained by <hi>Giving.</hi> And here, (beſides the rational conducible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Principles of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity and Bounty to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of mens temporal Eſtates, from the <hi>general Friendſhip</hi> which ſuch a Temper procures a man, whiles every <hi>mouth</hi> is open for him, every <hi>hand</hi> is ready to be lifted up in his defence, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to preſerve him as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick benefit; and the very worſt of men, that are wont <hi>vivere rapto,</hi> to live by cheating and robbery, have a great awe of injuring ſuch an one, as judging ſuch a Crime to be of a guilt little inferiour to Sacrilege:) I ſay beſides this rational Security, the munificent man hath the far greater Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Security of divers Promiſes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49298:30"/> of Divine Protection. <hi>If thou deal thy bread to the hungry,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,) and ſatisfie the afflicted ſoul; if thou bring the poor that are caſt out</hi> of their own, <hi>to thy houſe,</hi> and <hi>when thou ſeeſt the naked thou cover him, and hide not thy ſelf from thine own fleſh,</hi> i. e. any one that is parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of common humanity with thy ſelf, <hi>&amp;c: then ſhall thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs goe before thee,</hi> as thy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantguard, and the <hi>glory of the Lord</hi> (as the preſence of God to the Iſraelites in their march out of Egypt) <hi>ſhall be thy Rereward.</hi> And <hi>the Lord ſhall guide thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,</hi> into wayes of ſafety and ſecurity, and <hi>ſatisfie thy ſoul in drought,</hi> and <hi>make fat thy bones,</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt be like a watered</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Garden, and like a Spring whoſe waters fail not,</hi> when publick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities deſtroy the eſtates of others, as the ſcorching Sun doth the fruits of the earth in a dry ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50-138" type="pages">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49298:30"/>
               <p>Which <hi>Promiſe</hi> is the ſame in ſubſtance (abating the high Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors) with what (in plainer and more intelligible words, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Language of thoſe Times) we finde elſewhere thus expreſſed; that the <hi>righteouſneſs of him</hi> that is bountifull, <hi>ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for ever,</hi> i. e. he ſhall never be other, than a <hi>giver,</hi> he ſhall alwayes have wherewithall to <hi>give,</hi> and <hi>wealth and riches ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112. 3. 9.</note> (as conſtant inhabitants) <hi>be in his houſe.</hi> I could heap up many places of Scripture more to the ſame purpoſe. That of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet before mentioned, that <hi>by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 32. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>liberal things the liberal man ſhall stand,</hi> when others fall to decay. That of the ſame Prophet, that <hi>he that walketh righteouſly,</hi> (of <note place="margin">33. 16, 17.</note> which righteous walking Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving (as I told you before) is a part) <hi>ſhall dwell on high,</hi> (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſituation for ſtrength,) <hi>his place of defence ſhall be the muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of rocks,</hi> (not to be ſtormed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49298:31"/> or undermined,) <hi>bread ſhall be given him, and his waters ſhall be ſure;</hi> ſo as not to be ſtarved or famiſhed out of his fortification, placed in the Divine Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I forbear, that I be not too tedious in ſo copious an Argument.</p>
               <p>In a word, by this means that Quickſilver-wealth, that is ſo volatile, that ordinarily it <hi>makes it ſelf wings to fly away,</hi> (by offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 5.</note> Temptations to the owner to waſte it in riots and debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or to the Robber to take it away by fraud and violence) is fixed and kept conſtant to its Poſſeſſor: and <hi>uncertain riches</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 17.</note> (as the Apoſtle calls them,) being joyn'd with <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> (true <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Alms,)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 8. 16.</note> become <hi>durable</hi> and abiding.</p>
               <p>Whereas, on the contrary, the <hi>withholding what is meet</hi> from the good uſes wherein Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence calls for it, <hi>tendeth to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> is the ready ready way to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49298:31"/> undoe a man even in this world. For, (as conſtant Experience ſhewes) <hi>moſt men</hi> are wont to make little Conſcience, (when they have ability and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to do it,) of getting what they can from ſuch an one as is noted to be ſordidly tenacious; every one contributing either his wiſhes or his help to the pillaging of him: and <hi>Gods Curſe</hi> alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds ſuch attempts (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, as from men, juſtly,) <hi>blowing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hag. 1. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>upon</hi> ſuch Eſtates, till he hath <hi>blown them away</hi> (as your Margin in the place quoted reads it) which a ſordid Parſimony ſcrapes together, and holds faſt by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane contrivance and endeavour. Thus you ſee the <hi>Security</hi> that <hi>Giving</hi> yields to our preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, beyond <hi>Receiving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(2.) This <hi>Portion</hi> is rendred more <hi>comfortable</hi> to us in the <hi>uſe</hi> of it, by <hi>Giving,</hi> than by <hi>Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And this from a twofold cauſe.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49298:32"/>1. From the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> that a <hi>bountifull giver</hi> hath in his own Conſcience, that he ſpends out of that Eſtate which is clearly and entirely his <hi>own:</hi> a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which (how good a Title ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever one hath as to <hi>men)</hi> no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can have, as to <hi>God,</hi> but he. For whereas all our Eſtates are held of God as their Supreme Lord, (and that, under ſuch and ſuch charges and Duties to iſſue out of them to pious and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table uſes;) it follows, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe uſes be firſt duely ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, we have juſt reaſon to fear a forfeiture, and thereupon to queſtion our legal Title, <hi>in foro Dei,</hi> to the remainder. For, by taking from that Lump or Heap from which Gods portion is not ſeparated, we are in continual hazard of <hi>devouring that which</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>is holy,</hi> together with that which is our own propriety; <hi>i. e.</hi> of committing Sacriledge, which of all ſins doth moſt forfeit our ſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49298:32"/> and what we have to Gods Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer. Whereas, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the <hi>liberal Perſon</hi> that boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully diſchargeth all theſe Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is free from that ſcruple. For, as the <hi>paying of Firſt-fruits,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 26. 11.</note> under the Law, unto God, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the remainder of each years profits, to be freely and comfortably made uſe of by the Owner: ſo doth <hi>Almes,</hi> under the Goſpel, given proportionably to <hi>what we poſseſs,</hi> (as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our tells the Phariſees) make our <note place="margin">Lu. 11. 41.</note> whole Eſtates, in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious uſe, <hi>clean unto us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. From the true <hi>comfortable reliſh</hi> of the natural good which the Creatures afford with Gods bleſſing; which the <hi>ſordid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver</hi> never taſtes ſo ſweetly as the <hi>bountifull Giver.</hi> For (beſides that the great gatherers of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riches do many times through ſordid penuriouſneſs, deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as well as all others, the enjoyment of what they have,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49298:33"/> and have not the <hi>heart to eat</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>thereof;)</hi> it often falls out that <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> and other uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Paſſions which ſuch men are ſubject unto, when they do <hi>eat,</hi> make their <hi>bread</hi> to them <hi>like</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 102. 9. Prov. 20. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>aſhes,</hi> and <hi>fill their mouths with gravell,</hi> as the Scripture phraſeth the uncomfortable uſe of thoſe Creatures to ſome that are the comfortable food of other men. So that the <hi>bountifull man,</hi> whoſe generoſity ſets him above thoſe vexing diſtempers, enjoyes more of the Creature it ſelf in far mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er accommodations, than he that hath the good things of the world in the greateſt affluence, with the ſordid attendance of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting Paſſions that are wont to wait on penurious parſimony and <hi>covetouſneſs.</hi> So that <hi>a little</hi> (if it be but a little) <hi>that a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 37. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>(i. e.</hi> the charitable) <hi>man hath, is</hi> in this reſpect <hi>better than the riches of many</hi> ſuch <hi>wicked:</hi> And if, (for ſo it often falls out, as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49298:33"/> will by and by appear more fully) the <hi>Bleſſing of God</hi> upon bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full givers <hi>make</hi> them really rich; he makes them herein (withall) richer than all others of equal or greater Eſtates, that he <hi>addes no</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>ſorrow with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(3.) But the greateſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of all, (in reference to his <hi>Portion in this life)</hi> accrewing to the <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>religious Giver,</hi> is that which the worldly man moſt looks after, <hi>[Improvement and Increaſe;]</hi> which (even in mens Temporal Eſtates) is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired alſo by <hi>Bounty</hi> rather than by <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Parſimony.</hi> For indeed, though ſuch perſons as give liberally, are ordinarily ſaid to be <hi>too free to be fat;</hi> and the more a man takes from the heap, (in humane judgement,) he makes it ſo much the leſs: yet herein we often judge by falſe Meaſures, and might, if we duely weighed things, finde our ſelves as often confuted by Experience
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49298:34"/> it ſelf. For it is from thence, that thoſe ſpeeches of <hi>Solomon</hi> got the reputation of Proverbs, that <hi>there is that</hi> thus <hi>ſcattereth and yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 24, 25.</note> and that <hi>the liberal ſoul,</hi> though <hi>free,</hi> becomes <hi>fat</hi> (to croſs the <hi>former Sawe,)</hi> and he that <hi>watereth</hi> others, is <hi>watered</hi> (plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully with Gods benediction in the ſame kinde) <hi>himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence it is, that <hi>Giving,</hi> in the Scripture, is frequently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>ſowing,</hi> wherein the <hi>ſeed</hi> doth not (as one ſaith) <hi>perire,</hi> but <hi>parturire;</hi> it is not loſt, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated by the Soyl on which it falls, and made fruitfull; God <hi>increaſing</hi> to bountifull givers <hi>the fruits of their righteouſneſs (i. e.</hi> the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 3, 9, 10.</note> Eſtates which their Almes doe ſcatter;) and <hi>making all Grace,</hi> (that is, all ſorts of effects of his own Bounty,) towards ſuch <hi>to abound;</hi> and <hi>giving them all ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in all things;</hi> and even thoſe (among the reſt) of which they ſeem, by beſtowing ſo much
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49298:34"/> on others, to endanger the not leaving what is ſufficient for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>So that (as an ancient Writer tells us,) <hi>the breasts of Charity the more they are ſucked, breed the more milk;</hi> the Woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repta</hi>'s <hi>Barrel</hi> and <hi>Cruſe</hi> have no <note place="margin">1 Kings 17. 16.</note> bottom, whiles ſhe is charitable to Gods Prophet; and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of our Saviour, (in a ſort) is daily acted over and over, whiles, as in his, ſo in the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull donours hands, the <hi>loaves</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 14. 19, 20. 15. 36, 37.</note> as they are diſtributed, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</p>
               <p>Very ingenious, to this purpoſe, is the compariſon that one makes betwixt the Expences that men are at to maintain their Luſts, and thoſe that they charge themſelves withall to charitable Uſes; to the <hi>eating</hi> a Field of Corn in the blade, (as is uſual when it is rank,) by <hi>Horſes</hi> and <hi>Sheep.</hi> The teeth of Luſts in an Eſtate, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great, are like (ſayes he)
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49298:35"/> to thoſe of Horſes in ſuch a Field, that tear up the Corn by the roots; but thoſe of the poor, like the teeth of Sheep, that by crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it moderately make it ſpread and increaſe.</p>
               <p>And the ſtory <hi>Melancthon</hi> (as I find him quoted) tells us of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain good Biſhop, is very proper to this purpoſe. The good man upon a journey being compaſſed about by a crowd of poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (who, knowing his charitable minde, begged his Almes) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his ſervant that managed his expences, to give them <hi>three Crowns,</hi> which fell out then to be all he had in Purſe. The ſervant (conſidering the many occaſions that in travelling fall out) thought it good husbandry in his preſent circumſtances, to curtail the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Maſter, and ſave <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>three;</hi> withall, telling his Maſter how thrifty he had been for him. They had not travelled much further, when certain great
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49298:35"/> Perſonages meeting them, and knowing formerly the Biſhops bountifull diſpoſition, gave the ſame Servant for his Maſters uſe 200 <hi>Crowns.</hi> Which Bounty when his Maſter underſtood, he preſently expreſſed his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thus to his Servant for his former unſeaſonable Providence. Thou (ſaith he) haſt clearly loſt me an <hi>hundred Crowns.</hi> For thou gaveſt the Poor but two Crowns when I bade thee give three: and now God hath ſent me but two hundred: <hi>ſi autem tres de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſses, trecentos accepiſſes,</hi> if thou hadſt given the third Crown too, theſe two hundred had been three.</p>
               <p>Be the credit of the ſtory with the Author or Relater: but I am ſure, the <hi>Moral</hi> of it, (if it be a <hi>fable,)</hi> is good, and fully to our preſent purpoſe; to ſhew how mans Bounty engageth God's; and we never loſe more, than by what we think we ſave from pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49298:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> and charitable Uſes to adde to our own Eſtates.</p>
               <p>And the Reaſon upon which this great Truth is bottomed, is this; that (as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us) <hi>he that hath pity upon the Poor</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 19. 17.</note> doth, (in the rendring of the Vulgar out of the 72.) <hi>Domino foenerari;</hi> he lends upon <hi>uſury to the Lord,</hi> who is the beſt Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and ſure in ſuch caſes to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay</hi> the Principal Money with ample Intereſt; even to an <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold in this life</hi> (as his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 29.</note> runs, verified in the former ſtory) beſides the Intereſt upon Intereſt, accumulated, in <hi>life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas, on the other ſide, the <hi>hoording receiver</hi> (as St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> again tells the Rich man in the Goſpel) <hi>neſcit ſtruere divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias,</hi> is indeed ignorant of the true Art of thriving which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth; for he takes the wrong way to Riches, whiles he deals only with men that may break,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49298:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> (by a thouſand accidents, as well as, which too often falls out, through a diſhoneſt Deſign;) and ſo often loſeth the Intereſt with the Principal; and refuſeth to truſt God for his Creditor, who can never fail by caſualty, and (to be ſure) never will by deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and couſenage.</p>
               <p>And thus have you ſeen, by what I have ſaid, that (even in <hi>this Life)</hi> the Concerns of the <hi>Giver</hi> (as to point of <hi>Profit)</hi> are in a better Condition every way, than thoſe of the <hi>Receiver.</hi> And they are no leſs ſo</p>
               <p>2.) In <hi>Sickneſs and Death.</hi> For whereas the <hi>ſordid Receiver</hi> uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath a dolefull and uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Time of it, and receives the <hi>ſentence of death in himſelf</hi> with a great deal of horrour; whiles (partly) the omiſſion of the good that was <hi>in the power of his hand</hi> to have done, purſues him with guilt, and (partly) the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that he and his beloved
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49298:37"/> Mammon muſt now eternally part company, and nothing of all that he enjoyed can <hi>deſcend into the grave after him,</hi> afflicts him <note place="margin">Pſ. 49. 17.</note> with grief, and (partly) the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what he hath unconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably gathered diſtracts him with cares, and (laſtly) the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his Eternal Eſtate, which he hath formerly neglected, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth him with juſt and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved fears: the <hi>bountiful Giver,</hi> (if, at leaſt, he hath managed his Charities with Religious Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) either hath, or hath cauſe to have, an eaſie and peaceable Paſſage out of this world, a true <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in all reſpects. Whiles he is aſſured by Gods Promiſe, that <hi>he will ſtrengthen him upon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 41. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>his bed of languiſhing, and make all his bed in his ſickneſs:</hi> whiles the leaving his earthly goods lies not near his heart, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually kept the cares of keeping them at a diſtance from it; and the Conſcience of his good deeds
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49298:37"/> in this world, and the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſurance of the Friendſhips he hath made in another world, diſmiſs him hence with that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, which the vain Emperour <note place="margin">Auguſtus apud Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonium.</note> once fondly called for of thoſe friends which aſſiſted him in his laſt Agonies.</p>
               <p>3.) <hi>After Death:</hi> whereas there are are <hi>two things</hi> (in reference ſtill to this world) which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly men when they come to die are concerned for, (their <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> and their <hi>Poſterity;)</hi> both theſe alſo are ſecured to the <hi>boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Giver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(I.) His <hi>Memory,</hi> which <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 1:</note> tells us is <hi>better than precious oyntment,</hi> (to embalm and keep Men from putrefaction when they are dead:) the ſame holy Author tells us, ſhall <hi>be bleſsed.</hi> All men <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 7.</note> will ſpeak of ſuch an one with juſt commendations, and bury his Infirmities in his Grave, as think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves obliged to have his good deeds only <hi>in everlaſting</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:49298:38"/> 
                  <hi>remembrance.</hi> The good woman that ſpent her <hi>Box</hi> of <hi>precious oyntment</hi> upon our <hi>Saviours feet,</hi> received from him another <hi>oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> far more <hi>precious;</hi> in the aſſurance he gave her, that <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that Goſpel</hi> ſhould be <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>in the world, that good deed ſhould be told in memorial of her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But of the <hi>tenacious Receiver</hi> (whom in oppoſition to the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>righteous</hi> the wiſe man calls <note place="margin">Prov. 16. 7. <hi>ſuprà.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the wicked)</hi> he ſayes withall, that his <hi>memory ſhall rot,</hi> i. e. not only periſh, but alſo ſtink and be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive whiles it is periſhing, in the noſtrils of Poſterity: and though he take as great care as <hi>Abſalom</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 18.</note> did in his <hi>life-time,</hi> to raiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the moſt magnificent Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to preſerve his Name, when he is dead, yet they ſhall ſerve only (as they ſay his Pillar doth) to invite Survivors to caſt ſtones at, in deteſtation of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
               <p>(2.) His <hi>Poſterity,</hi> and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49298:38"/> Relations enjoy an entayled <hi>Bleſſing</hi> on the Eſtate which the liberal man leaves behinde him; and that in the largeſt extent that can rationally be deſired. And no wonder: For by his <hi>Charity</hi> he hath engaged God to be the <hi>Executor</hi> of his <hi>Will,</hi> the <hi>Husband</hi> of his <hi>Widow,</hi> and the <hi>Guardian</hi> to his <hi>Fatherleſs Children.</hi> And under his Tuition (the Pſalmiſt aſſures us, both by Promiſe, and anſwerable Experience to back it) they ſhall be well looked to. For (ſaith he) the man who is <hi>mercifull and lendeth,</hi> (ſometimes <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>lending</hi> is as true a Charity as <hi>giving) his ſeed ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> And he makes it good by an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental Obſervation of his own; <hi>I have been young and now am old, but I never ſaw the</hi> chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably <hi>righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging their bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas, the <hi>Poſterity</hi> of the <hi>ſordid Receiver</hi> have no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made for them, but (as to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49298:39"/> any Divine Promiſe) are left to the wide world, without any aſſurance of being thus cared for by him. So that (however they fare, when the Parent is gone, upon the account either of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Providence, or (if they prove better than their Anceſtor) by Divine Benediction as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their perſonal Piety; yet) the comfort hereof can no way lighten the cares and fears of his dying Bed: becauſe he hath no warrant to expect any better event to befall them, than the Prophetical Curſe beſtowed upon <hi>Judas,</hi> to be <hi>continually Vagabonds</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 109. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and begge,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Experience</hi> too often proves that Curſe to extend farther than the Perſon it was principally meant for; even to the Children of all thoſe who (like him) <hi>remembred not to ſhew mercy.</hi> It being a thing of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon obſervation, that the more the covetous Father leaves his Poſterity, the more certain Prey
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49298:39"/> they become to as covetous Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Guardians; or, if they eſcape them, are (too often) worſe handled by their own prodigal Luſts; which (before the third Generation) <hi>ſcatter all that with the forke,</hi> which the carefull Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor <hi>gathered with the Rake.</hi> So that frequently within one mans Memory a great Eſtate, in one and the ſame Family, is both gotten and ſpent; and ſpent in fewer moneths it may be than it was years in getting. It is an handſome Memento that one of the Ancients (before mentioned) gives the ſordid gatherer: Thou takeſt care, ſaith he, to oblige thy Heir by employing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of thy gray head to augment the Eſtate thou intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to leave him. Alas, Wretch, (ſaith he) thou art miſtaken. Thy young Spark <hi>odit incrementa hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditatis ſuae, ad damna feſtinat;</hi> thinks thou art getting too long, and would fain have thee make
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49298:40"/> an end of thy Trade of gaining, that he may begin his of ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what thou haſt already gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>And thus have I ſhewn you the advantage that in point of <hi>Profitableneſs, Giving</hi> hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Receiving,</hi> in reference to this world, and the Concerns thereof; both in <hi>Life,</hi> in <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>after Death.</hi> But the greateſt Inſtance of the <hi>Profit</hi> that comes thereby, is</p>
               <p>(2. In reference to the <hi>World to come.</hi> For (although there be no proper <hi>Merit</hi> in <hi>Bounty,</hi> how large ſoever, or however well qualified, to purchaſe everlaſting happineſs; (no, far be ſuch a thought from the breaſt of any charitable man;) for, <hi>our good</hi> in this life, be it what it will, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to God,</hi> as it muſt, if it <note place="margin">Pſ. 16. 2.</note> properly deſerve any thing at his hands: yet) whiles we <hi>extend our bounties to the Saints that are on earth,</hi> with ſuch diſpoſitions as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49298:40"/> God requires, we come under a capacity of being rewarded with eternal felicity, by vertue of his Promiſe; who hath aſſured us, that he will not <hi>forget our work</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and labour of love</hi> in this kinde: and if we thus <hi>ſow to the Spirit,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7, 8.</note> by taking <hi>opportunities of doing good, we ſhall of the Spirit reap life everlaſting.</hi> Upon the account of which ſecurity of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, a good man by his Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may have a ſtock going in another world while he lives, and when he comes to die, may tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, by <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Exchange</hi> (as it were) that cumberſome wealth, which no man can, (as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt <note place="margin">Pſ. 49. 17.</note> ſaith) <hi>carry with him</hi> in kind: and thus do our <hi>good works fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 14. 13.</note> us into Heaven which we did upon Earth; and the more they here <hi>abounded</hi> to the relief of others, the more will they <hi>abound</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 17.</note> there (as Fruits of the Spirit) to <hi>our account.</hi> When God and the truely charitable man come to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49298:41"/> 
                  <hi>reckon,</hi> (O happy reckoning!) with what infinite ſatisfaction ſhall he finde all his great and numerous <hi>Debts</hi> to Gods Juſtice by the blood and merit of Chriſt eternally <hi>cancel'd,</hi> and his <hi>good deeds</hi> only <hi>booked</hi> by God (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging himſelf by his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſe his debtour;) to be everlaſtingly rewarded; and that ſo punctually, that not ſo much as a <hi>cup of cold water</hi> beſtowed upon <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 41.</note> a charitable account ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
               <p>In this reſpect it is, that our Bounties are ſaid to <hi>make us</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>friends to receive us into everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing habitations;</hi> to wit, ſuch, as (in Gods name and for his ſake) <hi>receive</hi> from us: who, as they aſſiſt us whiles they live here, by their prayers to obtain them; and by acknowledging the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of what we beſtow on them in their thanks to God for us, do (as it were) give us thoſe Bills of Exchange which I before ſpake
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49298:41"/> of to draw upon God for them: ſo, when they die, and arrive at the ſame place of happineſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they perſonally atteſt to thoſe Charities they have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to make good our Title to thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Manſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thence it is, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (acquainting us with the form of the Proceedings in the laſt Judgement,) doth not only tell us, that our Charities will then be the great matters on which we ſhall be tryed: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, not obſcurely intimates, that the Teſtimonials of his poor mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers then preſent, will ſtand us in great ſtead, as our witneſſes; for ſo that phraſe ſeems to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, <hi>Foraſmuch as ye have done it</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 40.</note> 
                  <hi>for the leaſt of theſe my Brethren,</hi> (who are here ready to atteſt it) <hi>ye have done it unto me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas, on the contrary, the <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>tenacious Receiver,</hi> as he in his life-time loved his wealth too well to lay it out,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49298:42"/> though for the good of his Soul, <hi>(amator mammonae potiùs quam animae,</hi> in St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> phraſe) and therefore hath no <hi>good works</hi> there recorded, no <hi>ſeed ſown</hi> in that Countrey, to yield him any <hi>fruit towards his account:</hi> ſo he hath never a <hi>friend</hi> there to open his mouth for him, and give him a friendly Teſtimony in that Judgment. And, by conſequence, how rich ſoever he was in this world, he muſt needs be poor, and naked, and every way miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in another: <hi>having had all his good things in this life,</hi> (as the rich Glutton in Hell is told to his <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u. 16. 25.</note> eternal diſcomfort,) he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to lay claim to in the <hi>next.</hi> Yea, (which is infinitely worſe) as he hath <hi>ſhewed no mercy upon Earth,</hi> ſo in the other world he ſhall have <hi>Judgment without mercy,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 13.</note> and not receive a <hi>drop</hi> of comfort there, who denyed his very <hi>crums</hi> to his neceſſitous Brother here.</p>
               <p>And thus have I juſtified the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49298:42"/> Doctrine of my Text fully, by the <hi>foundations of Reaſon</hi> it ſelf upon which it ſtands: and ſo diſpatched the <hi>ſecond part</hi> of my intended Diſcourſe upon it. I come now to my <hi>third</hi> and laſt undertaking, to give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of</p>
               <p>III. The <hi>Inferences</hi> or <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> which it affords us, by way of deduction from it. In five Particulars.</p>
               <p>[1. It hence follows, that God hath put every mans <hi>preſent Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs,</hi> (at leaſt) in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in his own power.</p>
               <p>For you ſee, the <hi>Acts</hi> by which it is very much to be promoted in this Life, are within the reach of his own choyce; ſuch the <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Giving</hi> are: and if a man (withall) take care to perform thoſe Acts according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of true Chriſtianity, he may alſo thereby, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>lay up in ſtore for himſelf a good</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 6. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>foundation againſt the Time to</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49298:43"/> 
                  <hi>come, that he may lay hold on eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Will it be here objected, that the contrary ſeems to be the more proper Inference, <hi>[That God hath rather dealt hardly with the greater part of Mankinde, in that he hath put them rather under a neceſſity of Receiving than a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of Giving, by reaſon of the narrowneſs of their Eſtates, and incumbrances of their worldly cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances?]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> If ſo; I anſwer, (1) That the <hi>Giving</hi> in the Text extends not only to the donation of worldly wealth, but alſo, to all other wayes wherein one man may be gratuitouſly benefited by another; ſo that he that cannot <hi>give money</hi> or <hi>money-worth,</hi> is not excluded from this <hi>bleſsedneſs</hi> by his poverty; ſeeing there be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes of benefiting others, that put a man to no temporal expenſe. Our Counſels, and our Inſtructions, our Compaſſions, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49298:43"/> our <hi>Viſits</hi> upon many occaſions to expreſs them, our <hi>good words</hi> (many Times) to men, and our <hi>Prayers</hi> to God, alwayes; are reall and great Charities, where we have nothing elſe to <hi>give.</hi> (2.) That, even in reference to temporal Gifts, as there be few men, but often meet with objects more neceſſitous than themſelves; ſo there are few ſo diſabled, but by their labours they might, if they would, not only maintain themſelves, but alſo be ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided to allow ſomething out of their earnings to relieve thoſe who (either through age or impotency) cannot labour for their own ſubſiſtence. (3.) And that the greateſt part of thoſe whoſe temporall condition is ſtrait and uneaſie, yet diſable themſelves more by their Luſts. Thoſe Pence, yea Shillings and Pounds ſometimes, which divers ordinary Labourers and Handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftſmen expend in needleſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany-keeping,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49298:44"/> in Pride of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, and finer Fare than their condition and capacity will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allow; might amount to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Charities, if employed that way. (4.) And laſtly, that not <hi>actual giving</hi> only, but <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> and diſpoſitive alſo, where power is wanting, will reach the <hi>bleſsedneſs</hi> of the Text; God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the <hi>deſire</hi> which a man <hi>hath,</hi> in ſuch caſes, in ſtead of the performance, which a man <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>hath not</hi> in his own power. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>two mites</hi> are, from the <note place="margin">Luk. 21. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>poor Widow,</hi> accounted <hi>more,</hi> than the great Gifts of wealthy Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors. So that, though every man cannot in kinde equall the great charitable Donations of Kings and Princes; yet he doth not only equal but exceed them too, in Gods account, who hath a minde as large as theirs, though in a far meaner condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and <hi>gives</hi> (for generoſity) <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>as a King,</hi> though (for Eſtate)
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49298:44"/> he come ſhort of ordinary <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From all which, my <hi>firſt Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> appears not to be ill ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; that the good God hath put this <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> ſo far in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans power, that no man, if it be not through his own fault, is excluded from a capacity of obtaining it.</p>
               <p>[2. It hence follows alſo, that thoſe men are ſo far enemies to their own <hi>Bleſsedneſs,</hi> as the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of this Text extends; who wilfully diſable themſelves to <hi>give,</hi> and unneceſſarily caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon a neceſſity of <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and <hi>receiving</hi> too, in a moſt diſhonourable and ungodly way, as too many doe.</p>
               <p>(1. Such are thoſe (in the <hi>firſt</hi> place) who out of love to <hi>ſloath</hi> and <hi>idleneſs,</hi> chooſe rather to begg, or ſteal, than work for their living. Though indeed, as to this ſort of men, I needed not to have diſtinguiſhed betwixt <hi>beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49298:45"/> and <hi>ſtealing;</hi> as if all that did needleſly <hi>begge,</hi> did not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>ſteal.</hi> For, the Truth is, every luſty Beggar and ſturdy Vagrant is a <hi>Thief;</hi> even while he <hi>beggs;</hi> and takes no more than is volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily <hi>given</hi> him. For ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle plainly inſinuates, when he commands <hi>thoſe that ſtole to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>steal no more, but rather to labour with their hands that they may have to give to him that needeth.</hi> Whence it evidently follows, that he accounts him that was a <hi>Thief</hi> before, to be the ſame ſtill, and not to have left that Trade; who <hi>labours</hi> not, but lives upon the bounty of others, when by his labour he might put himſelf into a condition not to need it, yea, and to be able to contribute to others needs.</p>
               <p>And indeed, ſuch an one is not only <hi>one</hi> way, but <hi>many wayes</hi> a Thief: and commits a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Theft in every Alms he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49298:45"/>
               <p>(1.) He <hi>robs God</hi> of the Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes he beggs and takes of men for Gods ſake, as truely, as he robs his Neighbour, who in his name, without his order, takes up wares at any of your Shops. (2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>,) He <hi>robs himſelf</hi> of the gains which he might honeſtly make, and the Credit in which he might live, by a laborious Calling. And (3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>,) he <hi>robs</hi> thoſe that are <hi>true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poor,</hi> in divers reſpects: both by <hi>defrauding</hi> them of that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſubſiſtence, which they are entituled unto out of his own earnings, if he laboured as he ſhould; and by <hi>diverting</hi> into a wrong Channel the Charities of others, which belong to them, whereby he eats the bread out of their mouths, and wears the Cloaths that belong to their backs; and laſtly, by <hi>obstructing</hi> and diſcouraging the Incomes and Revenues of general Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which would be more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to the really neceſſitous, if
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49298:46"/> they were not overlay'd by ſuch ſupernumerary multitudes of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate and clamorous Beggars, that deſerve not an <hi>Almes,</hi> and yet will not take an <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(2. Such as take to that way of living, out of a falſe opinion of meriting thereby. Which is the courſe of all thoſe idle Drones and luſty Mendicants among the Papiſts, who make voluntary Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty a Religious Profeſſion, and place a great degree of Chriſtian Perfection in a Vow of continual Begging: as if they were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to give the flat lye to our Saviour Chriſt himſelf by invert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Text; and pronounce, (in direct oppoſition to him,) that <hi>it is more bleſſed to receive than give.</hi> Theſe Perſons are not only equally criminal with others of the Tribe of idle Vagrants and luſty Beggars, for breaking Gods Commandment, that appoints all men to live by the labours of an honeſt Calling; but far more
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49298:46"/> criminal than they, becauſe they blaſphemouſly entitle God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Patronage of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly and irregular living; and affirm that which is an expreſs breach of his Law, to be a work of ſupererogation, that is, of greater perfection than it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: and perſwade the poor people where they reſide, that to give to maintain their idle bellies, is an act of <hi>higheſt merit;</hi> whereas (indeed) it is the greateſt <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing</hi> of their Charity that can be, as being a direct abetting and encouraging them in a wicked and ungodly way.</p>
               <p>(3. Such as through prodigal Expenſes upon their Luſts and Debaucheries, caſt themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a neceſſity of <hi>receiving</hi> by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious living. Wherein, beſides the depriving themſelves of that capacity wherein Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence once placed them of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to their own <hi>Bleſsedneſs</hi> by <hi>Bounty;</hi> and the ſimple infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49298:47"/> which they draw upon themſelves of needing <hi>Alms</hi> from others, who were once able to have beſtowed them upon others: they expoſe themſelves likewiſe to the aggravated miſery of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving</hi> juſt reproaches with their relief, both from their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and the tongues of thoſe whoſe Charities they implore: and can hardly, without a great degree of impudence, dare to begg in Gods Name, who have reduced themſelves to Beggery in the Devils ſervice. To whom, indeed, (as to both the former ſorts alſo) your <hi>Bridewell</hi> is the moſt proper <hi>Almes-houſe,</hi> and the due Correction and Diſcipline thereof the moſt proper Almes. And yet,</p>
               <p>[3. It hence follows alſo, that no man ought to deſpiſe any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable object, whoſe true Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities call upon him for his Bounty: either by <hi>ſhutting up the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>bowels of his compaſſion from him,</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49298:47"/> or beſtowing the Charities he gives, ſo, as to clogg and leſſen them with opprobrious or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull circumſtances. And that, upon <hi>theſe conſiderations,</hi> which hold alſo from the import of my Text.</p>
               <p>(1. That whoſoever he be, that is preſented to thee as an object of thy Charity, gives thee, (whoever thou art,) an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of doing thy ſelf a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter turn than thou canſt do him. For how were it poſſible that any one could ever attain the <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>actual giving,</hi> if there were none to <hi>receive?</hi> And therefore, it is a mercy of God to the Rich, that he hath ſo ordered it by his Providence, that they ſhall <hi>have</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the poor with them alwayes;</hi> in that he thereby affords them dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſions, of making themſelves <hi>bleſſed</hi> by the continual exerciſe of their Bounty.</p>
               <p>(2. That if (as among many that are not ſo in theſe neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49298:48"/> times, ſome certainly are) any of the Petitioners for thy Almes be truely <hi>worthy;</hi> that which he returns to thee in thanks and prayers, is a <hi>greater gift</hi> than he <hi>receives</hi> from thee. For whiles he <hi>bleſſeth God</hi> for thee, and <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee</hi> in his requeſts to God to requite thee; he gives thee ſecurity of the repayment of that which thou giveſt him, with the greateſt Intereſt, out of Gods Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer. And though (it may be) thou knoweſt not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, when thoſe payments are made thee; yet thou haſt reaſon to believe, that the proſpering of thy worldly concerns (in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, if they go on proſperouſly) is a cumulative reward of thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Charities together; and (it may be, in particular alſo) thou oweſt the return of thy next rich adventure, or the ſucceſs of thy next gainfull Bargain, to the laſt poor mans Prayers that thou didſt relieve.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:49298:48"/>
               <p>(3. And, <hi>thirdly;</hi> that if he that asks thy Charity, be never ſo unworthy, upon whatever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, (even the worſt of thoſe mentioned in my former Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,) yet by that very <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs,</hi> (whiles his preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities require relief,) he gives thee an ampler opportunity of heightning thy <hi>generoſity</hi> by the hopeleſneſs of being ever requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him in any kinde; and herein rendring thy ſelf the more like to God himſelf; who takes it for a great addition to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his bounty, that he <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good to the unthankfull, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 6. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>cauſeth his Sun to ſhine upon the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>evil and the good, and his rain to fall upon the juſt and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[4. This Truth gives us wofull (and yet plentifull) occaſion to wonder at and bewail that Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs of the uncharitable Age in which we live; and the <hi>groſs Infidelity,</hi> or <hi>blockiſh Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49298:49"/> or both, of the <hi>great Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> the men of ample Eſtates and Revenues of the world. Their <hi>groſs Infidelity,</hi> if they believe not the Doctrine of my Text, ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively aſſerted by our Saviour, atteſted by ſo great an Apoſtle, and ſtanding withall upon ſuch fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m foundations of unanſwerable Reaſon, as I have before ſhewn you this, if any in the Bible, doth. And if they do believe it, and yet act contrary to the evident import of it, <hi>their monſtrous Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity;</hi> who are ſo little ſenſible of, or affected with, ſo great a part of their greateſt concern, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe rich <hi>Miſers</hi> (as they are moſt truely called by a Name moſt oppoſite to <hi>Bleſſedneſs)</hi> both my ſubject, and my inclinations, lead me here to proſecute with the ſharpeſt and keeneſt of reproofs. But I ſhall forbear, conſidering, that their own Conſciences (if they have any) muſt needs (upon
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49298:49"/> the Principles I have before laid down) do that work ſufficiently for me: at leaſt, that by their own tacite Confeſſion, they have cauſe to doe ſo, and they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſtand in fear that they will; ſeeing they meditate ſo many <hi>Excuſes</hi> to guard themſelves from their laſhes, as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly wont to doe.</p>
               <p>And yet <hi>(unhappy</hi> men that they are!) it fares ſo unluckily with them, that thoſe very <hi>Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> which they are wont to make uſe of to ſtave off all charitable motions ſuggeſted to them from others, and ſtifle their own work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of good nature, if at any time they ſtir, in their boſoms; doe only ſerve to declare how willing, and withall how skilfull and ingenious they are, to cheat themſelves of their own <hi>Bleſsed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And this you will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſee, (and they too, if their eyes be not totally blinded) by this brief examination of the moſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49298:50"/> uſual of them by the meaſures of this bleſſed <hi>Proverb</hi> of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> The <hi>firſt,</hi> (and that that is moſt ready in all their mouths, when any conſiderable Charities are ſuggeſted to them) is; <hi>ſuch and ſuch are better able to give than they, and they will firſt ſee what they give, that they may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> That is, (being interpreted according to the Tenour of this Text) either, that they are willing to make this great Complement to their Neighbours, that they are content to yield to them the precedency, though in point of <hi>Bleſsedneſs</hi> it ſelf; and think it <hi>good manners,</hi> (even therein,) to <hi>let their betters goe before them.</hi> But theſe men ought to conſider, that it is a dear and coſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, that loſeth a man an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of making himſelf <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> yea, or any way retardeth it.</p>
               <p>Or elſe, that they are deſirous
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49298:50"/> to have the price of <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> it ſelf beaten down by other Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, before they will deal in the commodity: which implyes, that they are afraid of purchaſing it for more than it is worth; a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that no man ever entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before them in matter of <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs,</hi> which generally men think to be well purchaſed at the price of all that can be asked for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> A <hi>ſecond</hi> uſual excuſe is, <hi>They are not the men the world takes them for; not ſo rich, or well to paſs</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>as they are reputed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Nor ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> neither, as they deſire to be reputed, if this <hi>Doctrine</hi> be true; who have an opportunity offered of making the beſt Bargain they ever made in their lives, for <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> it ſelf, and yet want an heart to make uſe of it.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Charities that have been bestowed by others before them,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:49298:51"/> 
                  <hi>have been miſimployed; and they will be ſatisfied that thoſe are better diſpoſed before they give more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> The true meaning of this excuſe is (being meaſured by the ſtandard of my Text) that they are unwilling to be <hi>bleſſed</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, till they can be aſſured that all the world is <hi>honeſt.</hi> And both, (if they continue of this minde,) are like to fall out to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>There are ſo many objects of Charity, that it is even oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the number; and it is to little purpoſe for a man to give to one or two, except he could give to all that need; for (at this rate) he cannot foreſee, if he once begin to be charitable, when he ſhall make an end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> That is, thou art ſorely <hi>grieved,</hi> that thou haſt ſo many opportunities offered to make thy ſelf <hi>bleſſed;</hi> and art afraid, that the taking hold of thoſe that are ſet before thee will draw on
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49298:51"/> more; ſo that thou ſhalt never make an end of <hi>accumulating bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs</hi> to thy ſelf. Is this a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal fear?</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Times are hard; Trading is dead; Customers break daily in their debts; they run great hazards in the ſmall dealings the hard Times afford them;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> Did ever rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture argue at this Rate? <hi>Times are bad; Ergo,</hi> 'tis out of ſeaſon to make my ſelf <hi>bleſsed. Trading is dead; Ergo,</hi> I am unwilling to deal in that Commodity, which yields the quickeſt and the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Returns. <hi>Customers break;</hi> therefore I reſolve to deal ſtill with breaking Cuſtomers, and not with God that can never break. <hi>I run great hazards</hi> in the Trade I drive; therefore I am loth to take the beſt courſe in the world to enſure my Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; the taking God into Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſhip with me in them. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended ſome perſons before to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49298:52"/> the Diſcipline of <hi>one</hi> of your <hi>Hoſpitals,</hi> that of <hi>Bridewell:</hi> And the men that argue at this rate, are as worthy to come under the Diſcipline of the <hi>other,</hi> that of <hi>Bethlem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>I have Wife and Children to provide for, and I think my ſelf obliged in the firſt place to take care of them: for if I neglect them, the Apoſtle tells me, I am worſe than</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>an Infidel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> That is, thou art deſirous to provide <hi>better</hi> for them, than to make them <hi>bleſſed;</hi> which, I have told you before, the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes and Poſterity of liberal men are. Nay (which is worſe,) thou art willing to bequeath them a <hi>Curſe</hi> in ſtead of a <hi>Bleſſing:</hi> to leave them an Eſtate <hi>blown upon</hi> and blaſted by divine maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet to look on this as a <hi>good Proviſion</hi> for them: which, it is (indeed) to be <hi>worſe than the worſt of Infidels,</hi> ſo much as to imagine.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49298:52"/>
               <p>Obj. <hi>I intend ſuch and ſuch Charities when I die, and therefore deſire not to be importuned till then in things of this Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> That is, in plainer Terms, (if my Text be true) that thou art reſolved to part with nothing, (no not for <hi>Bleſsedneſs</hi> it ſelf,) till thou needs <hi>muſt;</hi> that thou thinkeſt thy Executors fitter to be entruſted with thy greateſt Concern, (that of <hi>Bleſſedneſs)</hi> than thy ſelf, and art willing to hazard it upon their fidelity; That thou art afraid of being <hi>bleſſed</hi> till thou come to <hi>die:</hi> as if (contrary to the deſire of all mankind) thou thoughteſt it out of ſeaſon to foretaſte any part of it in this life.</p>
               <p>Did you ever hear any thing that pretended to Reaſon and Argument, more unluckily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing it ſelf, than all theſe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes</hi> that I have mentioned, do? And yet (ſuch is the folly of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did penuriouſneſs,) there are a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49298:53"/> great many more of the ſame bran, perpetually in the mouths of the men that are <hi>rich in this world</hi> (as our Saviour ſaith) <hi>but not rich towards God;</hi> which, though I mention not, yet (by the meaſures I have given you from this Text) you may (whenever you meet with them) your ſelves prove to be no leſs guilty of a like felonious deſtroying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>And now the fooliſh Mammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, that thinks to hide his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs with theſe Fig-leaves, may ſee, that if his own Excuſes taken up for his defence, thus fight againſt him in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men; they will be more killingly managed againſt him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgement-ſeat of Jeſus Chriſt: who is infinitely better able to manage the conſequences of his own Doctrine, than I or any other Preacher can; and will undoubtedly then ſhew all the world, what great Fools they are,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49298:53"/> that are ſo <hi>wiſe in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits,</hi> to evade the Duty that he requires of them, and cheat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>And are theſe, now, the men whom the fond world is ſo apt to admire as ſhrewd men, for parts and cunning contrivances to advance themſelves? whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples they ſet before their ſons; and whoſe <hi>ſayings</hi> they are wont to approve and quote as the great rules of living happily; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre <note place="margin">Pſ. 49. 13.</note> them before this and others of like nature, that are recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to them, from the mouth of their bleſſed Saviour, and the holy Pen-men of the Sacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures? Or, are they not rather perſons whoſe <hi>way is folly;</hi> whoſe <hi>ſayings</hi> (indeed,) are only wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be reckoned among the wild and extravagant diſcourſes of Children and Mad-men; and themſelves to be numbred, as the Spirit of God ranks them, among <hi>the beaſts that periſh?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">V. 20.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49298:54"/>
               <p>[5. It hence follows, that to <hi>excite</hi> and <hi>direct</hi> any mans <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> (how ungratefull ſoever this Office of kindneſs ſeem to ſome) is really an obliging courteſie; becauſe the intent of it is, (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly) to aſſiſt him towards the making himſelf <hi>bleſsed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which account (hoping I have here to deal with thoſe that will ſo interpret my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) I ſhall apply my ſelf (in the laſt place) to <hi>exhort</hi> you to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Actions, and <hi>direct</hi> you in the performance of them.</p>
               <p>(1. To <hi>exhort</hi> you, to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious practice of this Doctrine: to be mercifull, and bountifull, compaſſionate and charitable; <hi>rich in good works, ready to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>willing to communicate; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good to all men as you have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> obliging all the world, as far as in you lyes, by reall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and effects of diffuſive good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>To perſwade you whereunto, I
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49298:54"/> hope I ſhall need no other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, than (in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Text) I have already at large inſiſted on: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall only make ſome ſhort reflexions upon it to my preſent purpoſe, and leave it to you to enlarge upon them, (which I hope you will doe) in your private Meditations.</p>
               <p>(1.) And firſt, I intreat you from thence to inform your ſelves, what it is that I perſwade you to, Is it not, (that which you all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, as your very nature inclines you, to deſire above all things,) <hi>to make your ſelves bleſsed?</hi> Is it not that, which all men (though they take different wayes to it, according to their ſeveral ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions) do deſign and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue?</p>
               <p>(2.) Will you ſay, you agree with me indeed in the <hi>end,</hi> but you are not ſo well ſatisfied in the <hi>means</hi> I adviſe you to for the attainment of it? Does it ſtick
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49298:55"/> with you, that <hi>giving,</hi> (to which you are ſo averſe,) is recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the way to <hi>bleſſedneſs? Do</hi> I, <hi>therefore, ſay this</hi> of my ſelf, or <hi>ſaith not the Scripture the ſame alſo?</hi> View the Text again, and read there; <hi>[It is a bleſsed thing to give.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(3.) Is it an <hi>inferiour</hi> and <hi>leſs effectual</hi> means to the attainment of that end, than (that which the general practice of mankinde ſeems more to recommend,) the way of <hi>receiving;</hi> that is, of <hi>get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and <hi>keeping</hi> the good things of this life to your ſelves? Glance on it again, and it tells you far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>[It is more bleſsed to give, than to receive.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(4.) Does this ſeem an <hi>hard ſaying to you;</hi> a <hi>Paradox,</hi> which you are difficult to believe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Vouchers to aſſure you of the Truth of it? Look on once more, and you will finde, it is quoted, as the <hi>ſaying of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> an Authour beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49298:55"/> (eſpecially to Chriſtians, as we all profeſs our ſelves:) and one, who, (as I have before ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you) is the moſt competent Judge, in this caſe, of all men that ever were, or ſhall be.</p>
               <p>(5.) Do you queſtion, whether he indeed ſaid ſo, or is rather quoted as if he had ſaid it, to give reputation to that which had its original from an obſcurer Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor? Surely, you cannot be of that minde; when you look backward, and there read, that it is a <hi>ſaying</hi> attributed to our Saviour, by the <hi>great Apostle St. Paul,</hi> in a Solemn Viſitation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, before the <hi>Elders of Epheſus,</hi> whom he calls in as Witneſſes to the Verity of his Quotation, as I told you before; and knew, if he had falſifyed in that quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they were able to have confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</p>
               <p>(6.) Does it ſeem, (ſeeing it is only in this <hi>one place</hi> taken notice of,) to be a caſual word
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49298:56"/> dropped from him by the by, (as we ſometimes throw out Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes to maintain diſcourſe,) without Premeditation; and therefore uſed only once or twice by him; not frequently, much leſs conſtantly, as an axiome of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Verity? The very form of the Apoſtles quotation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes this conceit, for it is quoted, as <hi>Proverbs</hi> are wont to be, with an implication, that it was his familiar and conſtant word, for which he was noted, as govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his whole life by this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>(7.) Will you object (as we are wont to be very inventive when we ſtudy excuſes to ward off a Truth we have no minde to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain) that it was a <hi>ſaying</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) of <hi>his;</hi> but hardly thought great enough to be quoted from him, by any of thoſe Apoſtles that heard him, or recommended to Poſterity by any one but him that heard him not in perſon;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49298:56"/> they that did ſo, not minding it ſo much as to commit it to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory? The <hi>Text</hi> alſo confutes this fond conceit. For it ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to be famouſly known, even as far as <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and ſo noted, that it needed only to be <hi>remembred</hi> by them actually, as a conſtant motive to Beneficence, which they had long before trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured up in their memories no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, as a <hi>ſaying</hi> of ſpecial note and eminency.</p>
               <p>(8.) <hi>Laſtly,</hi> will you ſuppoſe, that the Apoſtle, (who then quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, as he had occaſion, to ſtir up the Charity of Chriſtians,) did, (as too many Preachers do,) preſs upon his Auditory a <hi>ſaying of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> which he, and his Brethren did not ſo far value themſelves, as to practiſe it in their own Perſons? Look then a little farther backward of the Text, and you will finde him there urging his own <hi>example</hi> and <hi>experience</hi> in the practical uſe of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49298:57"/> this Principle. For he appeals to all their knowledges, to atteſt, that his <hi>own hands</hi> (whiles he <note place="margin">V. 34.</note> preached the Goſpel freely among them) <hi>miniſtred</hi> (by daily labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>to his and his companions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities;</hi> and that he exhorted them not only to follow their <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Doctrine,</hi> but alſo his <hi>own example</hi> in conformity to it.</p>
               <p>So that you ſee, beloved, no ſtarting-hole is left (by the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent fore-ſight of the holy Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this Scripture,) for infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to eſcape the force and authority thereof: but every word and circumſtance ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to contribute more ſtrength and efficacy to it.</p>
               <p>And now, what ſhall I ſay more, what need I to ſay more, upon this head? If ſuch a ſaying, of ſuch an Authour, recommended to you by ſuch an Oratour, in ſuch an Aſſembly, in ſo ſolemn and affectionate a manner, and preferred by him to that place in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49298:57"/> his diſcourſe which was moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to commend it to the ſpecial notice and remembrance of his hearers, (the very laſt cloſe and concluding period of the laſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that ever he was to make among them:) I ſay, if ſuch a <hi>ſaying,</hi> ſo circumſtantiated, will not bear weight with you: it will be vain for me to imagine, that any thing ſaid by me ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added thereunto, ſhould be of any force or prevalency upon you.</p>
               <p>And therefore, (for a cloſe of this part of my Addreſs to you) I ſhall only recommend it to your own thoughts as a matter of ſerious conſideration, how you will anſwer it at the laſt day, when that bleſſed Apoſtle, that ſpake theſe words from the mouth of our Lord Jeſus, and that holy Evangeliſt who hath tranſmitted them on Sacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to us, (that I joyn not my ſelf with them who have all this
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49298:58"/> while been preſſing them upon you,) ſhall take up the Prophets complaint againſt you, and ſay, <hi>Lord, who hath believed our report?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 1.</note> Yea, when your bleſſed Saviour himſelf ſhall charge you with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, as thoſe in whom <hi>his</hi> own <hi>words have no place?</hi> How <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 37.</note> do you think, you ſhall be able to look him in the face, when it ſhall be objected to you before his terrible Tribunal, that the dirty Principles, and ſordid Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of a brutiſh ſort of World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Muckworms, have had more force with you for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of your lives, than his heavenly Doctrine, and glorious Example? that you never ſtuck at the gratifying your luſts with vaſt expenſes, whenever they called for them; and never drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped half-pence or farthings ſo penuriouſly on any occaſion, as when you were called upon in his Name and for his ſake to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a good work? that the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49298:58"/> of one room to beautifie your new dwellings, the expenſe of one Treatment to entertain your riotous Gueſts, the price of one Jewel or other coſtly Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to expreſs your vain Pride, the charge of one Moneths keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a caſt of Hawks or a ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of Hounds, for your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Recreation; yea, (which is far worſe,) the great ſtakes that you adventure upon one caſt of a Die, the value of one bribe to blinde the eyes of Juſtice, and promote a wrongfull cauſe, the Hire of an Harlot for one nights ſinfull pleaſure, and the like rates of other coſtly Debaucheries, <hi>(toties quoties,)</hi> a mounted to more by far, than all the ſummes, put all together, that all your lives long, you have beſtowed upon Religious and Charitable Uſes?</p>
               <p>Are theſe, my friends, are theſe the <hi>fruits</hi> that you deſire may <hi>abound to your account at that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Day?</hi> If they be, I fear, you will
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49298:59"/> make but a <hi>ſad account</hi> where ſuch <hi>Items</hi> make up the dolefull reckoning. Is this the way you take to <hi>make you friends to receive</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 16. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>you, when you fail, into everlaſting habitations?</hi> If ſo, I doubt, your Lodgings will be provided for you on the wrong ſide of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world: not in <hi>the Houſe made without hands, eternal in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Heavens;</hi> but the Furnace of <hi>everlaſting Fire,</hi> and the Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>everlasting darkneſs.</hi> Is this the way wherein you think <hi>to lay up in-ſtore a good foundation</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>for the time to come, that you may lay hold of eternal life?</hi> If it be, I am ſorely afraid, you will ſinde you have miſtaken your ground, and built your hopes upon <hi>the ſand without a foundation;</hi> as our Saviour tells us all thoſe doe, <hi>who hear his ſayings</hi> (of which my Text is one of the chief,) <hi>and do</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>them not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be, I have ſtood longer than needed upon this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49298:59"/> to thoſe, divers of whom, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in commendation of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>doni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 3.</note> are <hi>to their power,</hi> yea and <hi>beyond their power already willing of themſelves;</hi> who <hi>deviſe liberal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. 32. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>things,</hi> and need only to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed how they may reduce their own good inclinations to act, and purſue their bountifull intentions, in ſuch a ſort, as to make them moſt effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributary to the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> which my Text promiſeth them.</p>
               <p>Which, if it be ſo, (and I am willing in my Charity to ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy an Auditory to preſume it to be ſo;) gives me occaſion in the next place, to enter on my laſt task, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(2. To give you ſuch <hi>directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> in the purſuance whereof, you may amply experiment the truth of this Doctrine in your ſelves. All which (as you will ſee,) have ſo much countenance from the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelf, that you
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49298:60"/> may take them all for further <hi>Deductions</hi> and <hi>Inferences</hi> from it.</p>
               <p n="1">1.) The <hi>firſt</hi> ſhall concern the <hi>matter</hi> of your <hi>Charity;</hi> which muſt conſiſt of that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>your own to give.</hi> The <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> of Charity <hi>that you diſperſe abroad,</hi> and the <hi>rivers that</hi> (like your New River) you derive <hi>through the ſtreets,</hi> (to allude to that of <hi>Solomon</hi> in another caſe,) <hi>ought to be only your own, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 9. 16, 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>no ſtrangers with you;</hi> that your own bountifull Souls (the grand <hi>Fountain</hi> from whence they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,) may be <hi>bleſſed.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, God that <hi>hates Robbery for</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 61. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>a Burnt-offering,</hi> will never look upon your <hi>good deeds</hi> of this kind as <hi>ſacrifices wherewith he is well</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>pleaſed.</hi> There is a <hi>Curſe</hi> upon all thoſe temporal <hi>bleſſings,</hi> which are the fruits of Theft and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, of Cheating and Couſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, of Bribery and Extortion; and (which is commonly leaſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49298:60"/> thought of) the Sacrilegious ſpoyls of his Church, and its Sacred Revenues: and <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> can never grow upon that Stock, that (like the worm at that of <note place="margin">Jonah 4. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Jonas</hi> his Gourd) hath <hi>Gods Curſe</hi> at the <hi>root</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the palpable Cheat that the very Deſign of reaping <hi>bleſsedneſs</hi> to a mans ſelf from that <hi>ſeed</hi> which is ſtolne out of his Neighbours Barn, does imply; is ſuch a mockery of God, (who in ſuch matters is <hi>not to be mocked,)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7.</note> that ſuch a <hi>Giver</hi> (as <hi>Jacob</hi> did when he attempted in his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Garments to rob him of his Fathers Benediction) may rather fear he ſhall by that very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, (if he were never ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of it before,) <hi>bring a Curſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>upon himſelf rather than a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2.) The <hi>motives</hi> of it, muſt be <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> For it is from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that the <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> muſt be expected: and he that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49298:61"/> ſeeks <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> from <hi>Chriſts Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> muſt govern himſelf by <hi>his Precepts:</hi> as in all other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, ſo in the ends and motives upon which he ſeeks it. Now thoſe muſt be; pure obedience to the Command of Chriſt, and <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 3. Heb. 13. 16. Mat. 5. 16.</note> Faith of being accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in him; the <hi>glory of our Father which is in heaven,</hi> and the <hi>cauſing through</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 11, 12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>our rich bounty thanksgivings to him to be abundant;</hi> the <hi>profeſſing our ſubjection to the Goſpel of Chriſt; the walking worthy of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord to all pleaſing by our fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in every good work;</hi> the <hi>ſhewing our Faith;</hi> the <hi>adorning</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Doctrine of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 10. 1 Tim. 2. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Profeſſion of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and the like motives and deſigns of Charity, we finde recommended to Chriſtians, by our Saviour and his Apoſtles; by which we ought to direct our intentions therein, that we may be <hi>bleſſed in our deed.</hi> But where
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49298:61"/> the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> learns thoſe, which in the greateſt Charities they boaſt ſo much of, have uſually the greateſt Influence, (the <hi>obtaining the pardon of ſins,</hi> the <hi>delivering their own and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Souls out of Purgatory,</hi> and <hi>the meriting of Eternal Life,)</hi> I know not. I am ſure, they have little countenance from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: which, as it knows no <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and therefore directs no ſuch means to any one to get out of it; ſo, can no expreſſions be found therein, that give any juſt countenance to expect either <hi>pardon of ſins, or eternal life,</hi> as the merit of our Charities. For, if (as the Papiſts plead) the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture bids us <hi>break off our ſins by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 27</note> 
                  <hi>righteouſneſs, and our iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor;</hi> yet it is only, (as in <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars</hi> caſe) the changing a courſe of oppreſſion and unjuſt violence by Repentance into that of Charity and Beneficence,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49298:62"/> which is there intended. If it tell us, that <hi>Charity hideth a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>multitude of ſins,</hi> it means only preventively, in reference to the paſſionate effects of an unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table temper which <hi>stirreth up ſtrife,</hi> as the oppoſition in <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 12.</note> Text whence it is quoted, interprets it. And to all other ſuch places of Scripture, it ſelf gives us this one grand Barre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt expounding them to that Popiſh ſenſe, that it tells us, that God hath appointed us another ſufficient <hi>Propitiation for our ſins,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 2.</note> who hath undertaken <hi>by himſelf,</hi> (and therefore needs not our Charities to aſſiſt him in this work) <hi>to purge them.</hi> And if it <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> allow us (as a ſecondary end) to have a reſpect to <hi>Eternal Life</hi> in our good deeds of this kinde, yet it is only in order to the <hi>diſpoſing</hi> our ſelves for it, by ſuch actions as <hi>perfect</hi> and improve us <note place="margin">Col. 3. 14.</note> in Chriſtianity, of which <hi>Charity</hi> in its full latitude is one; and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49298:62"/> not to encourage us in a fond opinion of <hi>meriting</hi> it by them. For it withall tells us, that we muſt receive the very <hi>reward</hi> of our good works as a <hi>Gift,</hi> not <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note> as <hi>Wages,</hi> from God; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, when we have <hi>done all,</hi> (if we could do all) that we ought, in this or any other kind, that we are even then but <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 17. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſervants;</hi> and laſtly, that we muſt look to <hi>be ſaved not by works of righteouſneſs which</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>we have done, but of Gods mere grace and mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3.) The <hi>manner</hi> in which our <hi>Charities</hi> muſt be peformed, ſhall be the matter of my <hi>third Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> And that includes <hi>theſe particulars:</hi> Which alſo receive like countenance from the Text.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Readineſs</hi> and <hi>voluntary forwardneſs</hi> of Minde, which (as I told you before) the Apoſtle ſo highly commends in the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians;</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 3, 10.</note> to whom he propounds
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49298:63"/> their example, for their farther encouragement. And this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently follows from the Doctrine contained in my Text. For there can be nothing more abſurd, than to pretend a belief, that it is ſo great a <hi>bleſſedneſs to give;</hi> and yet to need to be forced by Law, or conſtrained by importunity thereunto: ſeeing there is nothing toward which we move with more freeneſs, than that that (we underſtand or believe) tends to make us <hi>bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Speedineſs</hi> and <hi>Celerity. Solomon</hi> requires us, in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not to ſay to an indigent Neighbour, <hi>Goe, and come again,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 3. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>and to morrow I will give;</hi> and we are required by the Apoſtle, not to let ſlip the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon or <hi>opportunity of doing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>good;</hi> than which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a quicker motion, or will ſooner ſlip by us if neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and therefore it ought in all dutyes to be <hi>redeemed,</hi> by a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 16.</note>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49298:63"/> taking hold of it. And this (ſaith <hi>Seneca)</hi> is an argument of our <hi>unwillingneſs</hi> to ſuch bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acts, when we are ſlow in doing of them. <hi>Qui tardè fecit beneficium, diu noluit.</hi> This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection alſo followes from the Text. For it implies a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, for any one to <hi>move ſlowly</hi> to that wherein he looks for <hi>Bleſsedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) <hi>Simplicity,</hi> or <hi>ſingleneſs of heart,</hi> muſt be another Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in all our acts of Charity; which diſclaims all by-ends and deſigns folded together with thoſe true Chriſtian ends which (I before told you) we ought herein to confine our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. He that gives for <hi>ostentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>vain-glory,</hi> or any ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous project, and <hi>blowes</hi> (with the <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 1, 2.</note> Phariſees) a <hi>trumpet</hi> before his <hi>Almes,</hi> to call ſpectators, <hi>hath his Reward,</hi> ſaith our Saviour; <hi>i. e.</hi> forfeits the <hi>true bleſſedneſs</hi> his Bounty would otherwiſe yield
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49298:64"/> him, by an imaginary felicity he takes in the <hi>vain applauſe of men.</hi> He that <hi>gives</hi> with a <hi>covetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> (as ſome do) to thoſe from whom he hopes to <hi>receive</hi> in the like kinde, makes <hi>receiving,</hi> his <hi>bleſſedneſs;</hi> not <hi>giving:</hi> becauſe he makes that the <hi>end</hi> and this the <hi>means.</hi> Now that hath not in it the true nature of <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that needs any thing elſe to make it deſirable.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) <hi>Plentifulneſs,</hi> and <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</hi> So the Apoſtle directs the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to extend their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 5.</note> as a <hi>matter of Bounty not of Covetouſneſs.</hi> Not, as if we were to <hi>buy a mean commodity</hi> in the Market, wherein we are wont to beat down the Price as low as we can, even to halfpence and farthings: but as we would bid for a Pearle of ineſtimable value, which men think well bought at whatever rate: or as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitours bade for the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> (in its later Age when the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49298:64"/> Praetorian Souldiers made their markets of it,) that ſtuck at no ſummes to out-bid each other. For ſo <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> deſerves to be purchaſed: he that under-rates it, is never likely to obtain it. <hi>He that ſoweth ſparingly</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, in this Argument,) <hi>ſhall reap ſparingly, and he which ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>bountifully ſhall reap bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> A <hi>narrow-hearted giver,</hi> is as fooliſh, as he that from a few grains of Wheat expects to reap an Harveſt like the rich mans in the Goſpel, that was fain to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his <hi>Barns</hi> to receive his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance.</hi> We muſt not (ſaith the Apoſtle <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 9.</note> alſo, in this affair) be <hi>weary of well-doing.</hi> Our <hi>goodneſs</hi> muſt herein imitate Gods, which (as the Pſalmiſt tells us) <hi>endureth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 52. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt ſowe our ſeed of Charity in the morning of our life,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and in the evening we muſt not withhold our hand.</hi> And this alſo
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49298:65"/> follows from the Doctrine of the Text. For that which we moſt deſire in <hi>bleſsedneſs,</hi> (and which, indeed, compleats it,) is <hi>duration.</hi> And therefore thoſe acts by which it is attained, cannot rationally be weariſome; ſeeing <hi>laſſitude</hi> can never be a companion of <hi>felicity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4.) The <hi>Meaſures</hi> and <hi>Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of your <hi>Chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> ſhall fill the <hi>last place</hi> in theſe <hi>Directions.</hi> And thoſe alſo are not obſcurely to be determined, from the import of this Doctrine. And that both</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In general, and</item>
                  <item>2. In ſpecial.</item>
               </list>
               <p>(1.) In <hi>general;</hi> for the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioning</hi> all your <hi>Charities,</hi> you ought to conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Your <hi>own Abilities:</hi> and thoſe not meaſured by the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Pride, Covetouſneſs, and unbelieving diſtruſt of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; but by the rules of Chriſtian prudence, conſidering all thoſe circumſtances which the condition of your affairs is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49298:65"/> withall. For he that <hi>gives much,</hi> in compariſon with others that are beneath him (it may be far more) in Eſtate; and yet <hi>little,</hi> in compariſon of what he might afford: <hi>withholdeth</hi> (in <hi>Solomons</hi> Phraſe) <hi>more than is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>meet,</hi> and deſerves <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> ſhould be meaſured to him, by the ſame <hi>ſcanty meaſure.</hi> And he, that by <hi>giving</hi> more than he can well ſpare, diſables himſelf to <hi>give,</hi> deprives himſelf of ſo much <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs</hi> for the <hi>future,</hi> as he loſeth of the capacity he had, of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing bountifull.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Receivers juſt capacity;</hi> all his circumſtances alſo being duely weighed in the ſame ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of Chriſtian Prudence. For by <hi>giving too</hi> largely upon <hi>one occaſion,</hi> a man is neceſſitated ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times to loſe many <hi>future oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions</hi> of advancing his <hi>bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in the way we are ſpeaking of: and by <hi>giving too little</hi> to any one, he loſeth the <hi>preſent opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:49298:66"/> or at leaſt improves it not to the beſt advantage to that end.</p>
               <p>(2.) In <hi>ſpecial,</hi> for the <hi>propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning</hi> of particular Bountyes and Charities, as they are to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly ordered, both in <hi>preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and <hi>quantity,</hi> according to the different obligations which reſult from the diverſity of objects and occaſions: there are theſe <hi>farther Rules</hi> to be obſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God, and our Countrey, our Parents, and our Children, and other near Relations, our former Benefactors and their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, our Neighbours and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and among them <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thoſe of the houſhold of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>faith,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and not wonted to begge, but under ſome preſent providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial exigency; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to have (in their ſeveral circumſtances proportionably,) the <hi>cream</hi> and chief of our Bounties; and the largeſt meaſures of it too. And from thence, we muſt deſcend to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49298:66"/> all men, Chriſtians and Heathens, worthy and unworthy, that are partakers of the ſame <hi>common hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity</hi> with us.</p>
               <p>For the nature of the Soyl, on which we <hi>ſowe</hi> to <hi>reap bleſsedneſs,</hi> (though no Soyl be altogether barren) is to be conſidered by the Seedſman; and the more fruitfull it is likely to be, the more ſeed is to be committed to it. Now, ſeeing all our good deeds of this kinde are ſo far contributary to our <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi> as they are <hi>accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God,</hi> and approved by our own Conſciences; and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of both theſe is our <hi>Duty:</hi> therefore where in Duty we are obliged to give <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>moſt,</hi> we may expect a more early and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Harveſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Publick Charities are to be preferred before private; and to do good to many, is more to be choſen, than to confine a mans Beneficence to a few. The <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs</hi> that reſults from <hi>Bounty,</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:49298:67"/> (like the beams that are reflected from an enlightened Body,) is more or leſs large and plentifull, according to the largeneſs of the object upon which it falls. And indeed, ſeeing the publick Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactour, (of all men) is moſt like God, (the Sphere of whoſe Bounty is of equal dimenſions with the whole world;) he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuppoſed to approach leſs to him in <hi>Bleſsedneſs</hi> than he doth in <hi>Bounty:</hi> eſpecially conſidering, that he is moſt communicative of himſelf, to thoſe that moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Perpetual Charities are to be preferred before thoſe that are of ſhort continuance. I mean, ſuch as are beſtowed upon Churches, Colledges, Schools, Hoſpitals, Almes-houſes, and all other ſuch uſes as endure to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Ages, and (as far as the Donours intention and deſign can reach it,) to the end of the world. I ſay, as far as the Donours deſign
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49298:67"/> can reach it; becauſe I know too often, thoſe Charities that were intended to be immortall, are by the unfaithfulneſs or ſacrilegious Covetouſneſs of after Ages im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezelled and perverted to private uſes: though (yet) that ſhould diſcourage no mans Bounties, ſeeing God judgeth of them, by the <hi>intendment</hi> of the <hi>Giver,</hi> not by the <hi>effect</hi> of the <hi>Gifts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which it was not in the power of the Giver perpetually to ſecure. And the reaſon why Charities of this nature are to be ſo preferred, is (by a fair Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the Text alſo,) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>perpetual Charities</hi> bear the beſt proportion to that property of <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> (to which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute) which I told you before, conſummates it; that is, <hi>Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity.</hi> For as to our <hi>memory,</hi> (which is the greateſt <hi>bleſsedneſs,</hi> which we are capable of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuating in this world) this is the way to engage <hi>all generations to</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:49298:68"/> 
                  <hi>call us bleſsed.</hi> And, as to our <hi>Souls,</hi> and the condition of them in another world; it may on fair grounds be preſumed, that the bountifull rewarder of our good works, will proportion the extent of the reward to that of the work, and make perpetual additions of happineſs to thoſe in Heaven, whoſe Charities perpetually grow upon earth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Charities to Mens Souls, are to be preferred before thoſe that extend only to their Bodies. For he is the <hi>greateſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactour</hi> to any one, that doth him the <hi>greateſt good;</hi> which is, certainly, the <hi>ſaving of his Soul.</hi> And then, it follows from the Text, that the greater the good is that any man does to another, the greater is the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> that reflects from it: as that <hi>Oven</hi> that is moſt intenſely heated, ſends back a <hi>greater</hi> and more intenſe heat upon him that heats it, than that which is made hot in a lower degree.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:49298:68"/>
               <p>And thus, I have done with my Text, both as to <hi>the Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Terms,</hi> the farther <hi>confirmation of its Truth,</hi> and the general <hi>Inferences</hi> ariſing from it. And what now remains, but to cloſe up this Diſcourſe with a word of <hi>particular Application</hi> to your ſelves, and your preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions?</p>
               <p>It is a thing notoriouſly known, that (for theſe <hi>three</hi> ſorts of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> laſt mentioned) this <hi>famous City</hi> hath in all Ages paſt yielded abundance of <hi>bleſſed Benefactors;</hi> as appears in the many <hi>publick Monuments</hi> thereof: and thoſe ſo ordered, as to be <hi>perpetual</hi> Reliefs both to the <hi>Bodyes</hi> and <hi>Souls</hi> of Men, to all ſucceeding Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And I no wayes doubt, but that the Names of many of the preſent Age, will be added to their worthy Predeceſſors, and tranſmitted, with like Honour to Poſterity.</p>
               <p>And though we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49298:69"/> that you the worthy <hi>Trustees</hi> for the ſeveral <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> of this City, deſerve to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned among the <hi>bleſſed Givers</hi> in the Text, though you <hi>give</hi> them no more than you daily do when juſt occaſion requires; to wit, your <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> your <hi>time</hi> and <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>pains,</hi> which you might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe employ to your worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and laſtly, your <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>faithfull care</hi> in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Truſts, with no profit or emolument thence accrewing to your ſelves: yet it is to be hoped, that you will alſo <hi>bleſs your ſelves</hi> yet farther, by adding, of your <hi>own Donation,</hi> to the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, which you govern and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage for your Predeceſſors.</p>
               <p>And, in ſpecial, (as my preſent Relation obligeth me) give me leave, (not with any deſign to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct or diſcourage any ones good Inclinations to the reſt, for the effects of the late dreadfull Fire,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49298:69"/> have been ſo univerſal that they have all need enough) to minde you more particularly of your <hi>two Hoſpitals</hi> of <hi>Bridewell</hi> and <hi>Bethlem;</hi> too much (it may be) of late forgotten, in the ſubſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary Charities of particular Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, though they are inferiour to none in the uſes they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for; and (it may be too) in ſome reſpects, of greater pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick uſe and advantage than any of the reſt.</p>
               <p>For in the <hi>one</hi> of them (that of <hi>Bethlem,</hi> the only Hoſpital, as I underſtand of that kinde in the three Kingdoms) the conſtant Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities which you therein diſpenſe, <hi>imitate the very creating goodneſs of God,</hi> in the ſucceſsfull means that are uſed for the reſtoring (not of mens lamed and maimed limbs, and members, as in ſome other of your Hoſpitals, but) of Humanity it ſelf, to abundance of miſerable Creatures, (and the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49298:70"/> more miſerable for that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not their own miſery, but rather delight and glory in it, and reſiſt as far as they can, the means of their recovery;) who retain nothing of man, but ſhape and voyce, to difference them from the worſt of Brutes: whoſe <hi>underſtanding and reaſon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 34, 36.</note> 
                  <hi>returning to them</hi> (as <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi>'s did when he was cured of a like diſtemper) bleſs God (and you under him the bleſſed means thereof,) for their reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>other,</hi> (that of <hi>Bridewell,)</hi> beſides the <hi>imitation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting and renewing Grace of God,</hi> (as far as juſt ſeverities can effect it, and we have no reaſon to think them altogether ineffectual, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture tells us, that the <hi>rod and reproof,</hi> are means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 15.</note> to <hi>give wiſdom;)</hi> in the recovering and reclaiming noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>ſinners from the errour of</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:49298:70"/> 
                  <hi>their wayes, and ſaving their ſouls from death,</hi> wherein the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> placeth a great part of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: <note place="margin">Jam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ult.</note> you alſo ſtrive to <hi>reſemble</hi> his <hi>preventing Grace</hi> likewiſe by the conſtant care taken, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made therein, for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian education of many miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly neceſſitous Children in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Trades and employments; wherein they may get their live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood by labour, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, (being trained up to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe of life but Begging or Thieving,) would be endangered to an almoſt inevitable ruine both of Body and Soul.</p>
               <p>All of whom, may, through Gods bleſſing on your endeavours (though like the gueſts in our Saviours Parable, they be many of them gathered up by your Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers <hi>from the High-wayes and Hedges,</hi> and brought into your Government by neceſſary <hi>compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion)</hi> prove, as divers of them have
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49298:71"/> done, (who, to their own Honour as well as that of your City, and to the Glory of God principally, that directed and enabled you to make ſuch proviſion for them, have appeared and will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after (no doubt) Annually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to appear in publick to give proof thereof:) honeſt and ſubſtantial Citizens.</p>
               <p>A mercy, for which, (next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, and the general influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> and <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of this famous City) they muſt acknowledge themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely obliged to the Fatherly care, and diligent inſpection of a publick ſpirited, prudent, vigilant, and active <hi>Preſident</hi> (whoſe larger character I muſt forbear at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in tenderneſs to his modeſty) together with the worthy <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi> his Aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p>All that I have more to adde, concerning <hi>both Hoſpitals,</hi> at this Time, is, That, it is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49298:71"/> the <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi> you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready (according to my Text) found in your paſt Beneficences, will encourage you (beyond all the Rhetorick which, if I had it, I could beſtow on ſuch an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,) to go on, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually promote ſuch further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, as ſhall be ſuggeſted to you for the rendring them more uſefull to the ends of theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Foundations.</p>
               <p>And here give me leave, (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) <hi>firſt</hi> of all, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you, the <hi>New-Building,</hi> (among all the famous Structures that your City hath raiſed for publick uſes ſince the laſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fire) of your <hi>Hoſpital</hi> of <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> which I doe upon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that thoſe who have the particular Inſpection of that Hoſpital, (and eſpecially, that learned and diligent <hi>Phyſician</hi> who can hardly be valued ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently for his great skill, fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49298:72"/> and induſtry in that employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) have declared, that they judge it very convenient, if not neceſſary, (conſidering the great numbers that are continually ſent thither for cure) that their ſtrait Accommodations of Lodging, ſhould be enlarged both as to Capacity and Conveniency; but are diſcouraged in the purſuance of thoſe thoughts, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the great charge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of far exceeding the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its ſmall Revenues, (the ſmalleſt of any Hoſpital in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don)</hi> except they be aſſiſted by ſome worthy Perſons particular Munificences.</p>
               <p>And <hi>next,</hi> on the behalf of your other Hoſpital of <hi>Bridewell;</hi> it is not unknown to the moſt of you, that a very great part thereof was reſtored out of its ruines and rubbiſh, ſince the late dreadfull Conflagration, at its own charge: whereupon, their
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49298:72"/> whole Stock being exhauſted, and the Building (for a great part remaining) likely to be left unfiniſhed, they muſt for ever acknowledge the ſeaſonable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the <hi>Right Honourable</hi> the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> and the <hi>Court of Aldermen,</hi> towards the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Edifice, out of the publick Purſe; without which, thoſe <hi>Wastes,</hi> were like to have been <hi>Deſolations of many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet when that great work is throughly finiſhed, (which is now near done) there will (there alſo) be farther need of addition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al private Charities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> in order to the endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a School, (already as to the caſe, built,) for the improvement of the young Nurſelings of your Charity, the <hi>Blew Boyes,</hi> in Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Writing, and caſting Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at ſuch hours as ſhall be aſſigned by the Governours,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49298:73"/> with the leaſt intrenchment that may be, upon their Maſters oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. Which, if it were once effected, it is not to be doubted, but ſome of them that are of riper Capacities, having their educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thus heightened, would when they come out of their time, be enabled to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to more beneficial and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous imployments, than they can expect the mean Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures they are there bred to, will afford them.</p>
               <p>And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> in order to the more liberal rewarding of the moſt honeſt and induſtrious of them, when they have faithfully ſerved their Apprentiſhips, with ſuch an concouraging Stock to ſet up withall; as might enter them into their new Callings with an hopefuller proſpect of carrying them on in a thriving and creditable way. Upon which expectation they would (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs)
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49298:73"/> more generally be induced, to acquieſce in the ſervices allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, more contentedly, follow their buſineſs more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and carry themſelves, (in hope of their good word at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to recommend them to your Bounty) to their Maſters more dutifully: and not be tempted, (as too many daily are, by the difficulties of getting a lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood by their Labours when they are free-men,) to run away, and return again to the worſe Trade they were firſt bred in.</p>
               <p>Theſe particulars, I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to ſuggeſt to your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, not to limit them to my conceptions, as if I knew better how to manage your Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than your ſelves; but only as probationers for your approbation and effectual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, in caſe, upon due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, you finde them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thereof.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:49298:74"/>
               <p>Now the Lord give you all ſo affecting a ſenſe of the Truths I have delivered concerning the <hi>bleſſedneſs of Giving</hi> above <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving;</hi> that you may be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of making experiment of it your ſelves: and then give you to finde it every way as I have taught you, in your Perſons, in your Houſes, in your Trades, in your Memories, in your Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; and principally, in your Souls, and their everlaſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, in the laſt and great day of our Lord Jeſus: <hi>To whom, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:74"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some Books Printed for and ſold by</hi> James Collins <hi>at the Kings Arms in</hi> Ludgate-ſtreet, 1673.</head>
            <p>OBſervations upon Military and Political Affairs, by the moſt Honourable <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle: Fol.</hi> price 6 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached by <hi>Seth</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> at the Funeral of the moſt Honourable <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle: Quarto,</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoſophia Pia,</hi> or, A Diſcourſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious tendencies of the Experimental Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, to which is added a Recommendation and Defence of Reaſon in the Affairs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by <hi>Joſeph Glanvil,</hi> Rector of <hi>Bath: Octavo,</hi> price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Way to Happineſs repreſented in its Difficulties and Encouragements; and cleared from many popular and dangerous miſtakes, by <hi>Joſeph Glanvil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prefatory Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Henry Stubbs,</hi> the Doctor of <hi>Warwick,</hi> by <hi>Joſ. Glanvil: Octavo,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Life and Death of Mr. <hi>George Herbert,</hi> the Excellent Authour of the Divine Poems. Written by <hi>Iſ. Walton: Octavo,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Forbearance of Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which a due Reformation requires, by <hi>Herbert Thorndike</hi> one of the Prebendaries of <hi>Weſtminſter: Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:75"/>
            <p>A Private Conference between a rich Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman, and a poor Countrey Vicar made publick, wherein is diſcourſed the Obligation of Oaths, which have been impoſed on the Subjects of <hi>England: Octavo. 2 s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Epiſcopacy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> juſtified to be Apoſtolical from the Authority of the Primitive Church: and from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of the moſt famous Divines beyond the Seas, by the Right Reverend the late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Dureſin,</hi> with a Preface written by Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton</hi> Baronet: <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Sermons preached before the King at <hi>White-hall</hi> by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Seth</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Catholick Charity recommended in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before the Right Honourable the Lord Maior of <hi>London,</hi> in order to the abating the Animoſities among Chriſtians that have been occaſioned by differences in Religion, by <hi>Joſ. Glanvile,</hi> Rector of <hi>Bath:</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Mirrour of Chriſtianity, and a Miracle of Charity; or an exact Narrative of the Life and Death of the Lady <hi>Alice</hi> Dutcheſs <hi>Dudley,</hi> by <hi>R. Coreman,</hi> D. D. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The General Aſſembly, or the neceſſity of the receiving the Communion in our publick Congregations evinced from the Nature of the Church, the Word of God, and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Principles; A Sermon by <hi>Francis Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> D. D. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49298:75"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſerere Cleri;</hi> A Sermon preſenting the Miſeries of the Clergy, and Aſſigning their true Cauſes in order to Redreſs, by <hi>Edw. Wettenhall,</hi> B. D. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rint &amp; Thummim;</hi> or the Clergies Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Duty recommended in a Viſitation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; by <hi>Mal. Convant,</hi> B. D. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Toleration, in Anſwer to a late Book, entituled, A Diſcourſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of <hi>England,</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indulgence not juſtified, being a Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Diſcourſe of Toleration, in anſwer to the Arguments of a late Book, entituled, A Peace-Offering or Plea for Indulgence; and to another, call'd, The ſecond Diſcourſe of the Religion of <hi>England,</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Toleration not to be abus'd, or a ſerious Queſtion ſoberly debated and reſolved upon Presbyterian Principles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Judgement of the Learned and pious St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> concerning penal Laws againſt Conventicles, and for Unity in Religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in his 48 Epiſtle to <hi>Vincentius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dead Mans Real Speech, a Sermon preached on <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. 4. upon the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>April,</hi> 1672. at the Funeral of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>John</hi> late Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Count Palatine of <hi>Durham:</hi> Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Brief of the Life, Dignities, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, principal Actions, Sufferings, and Death of the ſaid Lord Biſhop of <hi>Durham.</hi> By
<pb facs="tcp:49298:76"/> 
               <hi>Iſaac Baſire,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinanary to his Majeſty. price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Neceſſity of keeping our Pariſh-Churches, argued from the ſin and danger of the Schiſms in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and of the preſent Separations; in a Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Honourable Judges at the laſt Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes held at <hi>Exeter,</hi> by <hi>Francis Fulwood,</hi> D. D. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Holy Rules and Helps to Devotion both in prayer and practice: in Two parts: Written by the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>Bryan Duppa</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> in the time of his Sequeſtration.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
